All right.
>> And the password is capital Wyoming.
>> Tell you rest
>> 126.
>> Go ahead.
>> While they're while they're finish
getting that hooked up, I just want to
kind of introduce you to our moderator
tonight, Dr. Stuts. She is the senior
vice president of student services at
Larby County Community College. Her
responsibilities include oversight
of the infusion of career exploration
into academic planning and the college
experience prepared to students for
life. Here's the part that really
impressed me is uh the dean of students
is underneath her and I could have used
some advice couple of few decades ago.
So, thank you so much for helping us. Um
we really appreciate it. Um,
I've really just asked her to keep us on
the track, keep us focused as much as
possible. Um,
I I just talking to you all before
before we the last week or two. I don't
think this is going to be like five
years ago where we had things all over
the all over the walls. And I think
we're a little more focused on on what
our our goals are. Um, so that's good.
Um,
thank you Jennifer. She's set up all
this again. She stayed late last night.
She set up all this up today. Matt Matt
helped. So, thank you so much. Uh, thank
you, Mayor Collins. Appreciate all your
all your help, all your input. And if
this machine is working, thank you to
the citizens of of Cheyenne.
You support us, you challenge us, you
encourage us, and it keeps us keeps us
moving forward.
I asked uh Jennifer if we could include
the mission statement um just because I
don't see it very often. Maybe you do,
but uh and it's very brief. I'll read
it. The mission of this uh Cheyenne city
government is to provide our community
with the services necessary to promote a
desired and sustainable quality of life.
We are stewards of all that is entrusted
to us. I I highlighted the word desired
because I think we do a pretty good job
at at the sustainable part of it, but I
at least I feel we need to work on some
of the desirable part of it.
Um, so
hello council. How are you?
Um,
let me get my little cheat sheet out
here.
I also included uh behind that I
included the code of conduct. Uh Patrick
and I were on the council when this was
written and I think it was written
because we needed
>> but there are there are just a few
little parts of it that I would like to
go over
>> for me it's four pages for
>> and uh it was good for me to review it
again in the introduction.
Um, I just want to take this one
sentence if I can. The council as a
whole is a legislative body and as such
it is not the duty of the council to
administer the day-to-day administrative
operations of the city.
I need to be reminded of that at times
because I tend to go straight to a
department and ask them for things to do
things and honestly that if it's a new
project or something like that, it
really should go through the mayor and
go stack. So, I think it's just
important for us as we go through the
next year to kind of keep that in mind.
Um, it's their responsibility. I'm I
feel like I'm on the board of directors
and I really have no control over the
staff or anything else. So, that is part
of our code of conduct. Um,
let me see. I think I have one more
highlight there.
>> We probably need to retype this. It's so
old. Scott.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
well, I think I've already talked about
request for projects and and governing
body, how we conduct ourselves with
staff. So, if you desire at some point,
I think it's a two-minute read. I think
it is worthwhile.
Um
before we go into old business,
um all the projects we've worked on in
the in the last year, there are are
updates in there. I hope you've had a
chance to read those. We can certainly
talk about any of those that you'd like
to. Um,
I've over over time I've had a little
cheat sheet somewhere,
but I try to keep track of some of the
projects that we've worked on. And in
addition to what we've done in the last
year, I it's always amazing to me what
we've done in the last five years.
I've shared this with some of you
remember seeing this.
Um
just a few highlights for me when we all
all of us except um
Dr. Evans, Mr. Wolf,
and uh Councilman Moody were here 5
years ago and when we came at least when
we started the city had a 67day budget
reserve. They had just rifted employees.
We're in the middle of CO
>> and times were a little tough. And so
when I compare that to where we are five
years later, I'm proud of the fact that
we now have roughly a 280day reserve. Uh
we have not ripped any employees. We've
actually added employees. Uh we've added
at least 14 police officers, nine fire
officers. I know because of a lot of the
buildings going on in uh we've added
inspectors and plan reviewers and and so
in my my little world that I live in in
a 5year period we've really gone from
one extreme to the other and it's uh
it's really treated all your hard work.
I think you've done a lot changed the
UDC codes, created the TIFF. Um I mean
it's just if you sit down and look at it
and I like about it it's like how did
you ever do all this? Um, last year
2025, there were $35 million in road
projects. Uh, we purchased the beast,
built a gymnastic center. I mean, if if
you want a copy of this just to look at
it, remind yourself, I'd be happy to
make that for you.
Um,
let's open it up to uh last year's
goals.
Who would is there a discussion item
that anybody would like to talk about?
Any of the goals? We did ask uh Director
Cobb to give us an update on the 15th
and 16th Street projects which is under
package. Talked a lot about that last
night. I don't know if we want to go
over that again.
Um
no
anything on the old goals.
Okay.
>> Maybe I would like to talk just a little
bit about Reed Avenue. Um,
we know from talking to Mr. Todd that
we're probably um what 180 days away
from the U railroad giving us the notch
on our our plan. We we sent what a 30%
design and u they gave us
I don't know an acknowledgement that
that sounds like it might be able to
work and uh so now we've sent them the
whole thing and I said it take us about
18 months to get a final approval but
when that comes you know I would love
for us to be in a position that as soon
as that that final acknowledgement comes
that we're in a position to start
working on that project and Um,
we have 280 days worth of reserves. I
would love to spend, you know, four or$5
million of that on this project. Um, I
think some of the testimony I heard
yesterday is we made a commitment. Um,
we didn't realize when we made that
commitment, we didn't own the property
and um, a lot of different things that
went on with that, but over the last
five years, Mr. Cobb and a lot of work
has been done to, uh,
to start trying to get those approvals.
We I think all of us here feel like
we're in a good position that that
eventually will come. Um we have to
close four streets and we're have to
inconvenience uh some neighborhoods in
the process, but it'll improve safety in
the community. And um but I think maybe
it's not a goal that we need to do, but
I think as a federal body over the next
couple of months, we ought to try to
figure out a way to uh memorialize that
either resolution or or something that
that that's our goal. U as soon as we
get those approvals, we have an be ready
to go out on the street for that
construction and we can uh we can start
what is it called the prominade. Um you
know or at least part of Reed Avenue.
And I would suggest that at least from
20th Street North um might be might be
smart. A lot of the stuff to the south
is uh on the west side is the state
offices and and things like that. And
I'm not sure we're going to get a lot of
uh turnover um on those buildings right
away. But to the north, I think some
real great opportunities for economic
development and some opportunities uh to
really maybe improve the quality of life
in our area. So we're talking about that
project. I'm I'm excited about it. I
didn't know anything about it until Mr.
Lemore took me our tour almost six years
ago now. And uh I stopped thinking about
it. I think it's a good project and I'd
love to see us do it. And I think that's
what we saved money for was to take
advantage of opportunities when they
come. And I think this is one that we
should do.
>> Mr. President, um, Mr. Cler do have that
on my list. And, uh,
part of the discussion we had last night
on the road closures when engineer K was
talking about some of the projects he's
got in his pipeline.
What we didn't talk about was with the
18th Street that they're going to redo.
I'm assuming that it does go all the way
through down to
the Cro Creek area, right?
>> As well as the Missile Drive. So, both
18th and 19th Street will be east and
west,
>> correct?
>> I know. 18th Street will be I'm not sure
about 19th Street.
>> Well, it's 19th and 20th. East and west.
>> The oneways
>> the oneways are 19th and 20th.
>> Yeah.
>> What?
I didn't quite understand your question.
>> I thought that 18th Street was going to
be redone, but I didn't know how far
down he was coming with that project.
So,
>> um I know the uh historic drain goes all
the way to the to the creek. I don't
know where the where the road ends.
Honestly, I don't remember.
>> I think that's
any storage drainage.
>> Yeah,
>> right. We're going to redo everything.
>> And alter
>> I talked to um a gentleman today on his
way out from the DDA meeting and he was
a little uncertain um about the road
closures. He said he read your letter um
about the six penny sales tax ballot and
he took from that that we're not sure
that the road closures are going to
happen. I was under the impression that
as we were accepting this big TFR grant
the three million dollars that uh we had
pretty much already agreed that we were
going to do these road closures. So, I
think that I don't know how he read that
out of that memo, but I think there are
still people who believe that that is
not a final decision. I mean, that that
that that's not our intention. Um, and
that there's still room for discussion
there, but and what we're keep
presenting to the railroad and we're
paying them to review over and over
again is that those road closures are
part of that deal. Is that correct?
>> Yeah. I don't think it's finalized yet
because we haven't approved the final
final thing, but I think the will of
this governing body is that we want to
do the red corridor project and the
railroad has told us only way we're
going to do that is closing port road.
So, I think we I think it's a done deal.
>> Well, once we accept that money, it's a
done deal.
>> Yeah, I believe so. So,
>> but we have we haven't finalized
everything. We haven't done the final
contract, but I don't think anybody here
is going to vote no um to do that unless
Well, I can't imagine that we are. I
think we're that far down the road. So,
if you read that, I'm not sure I meant
it that way. I have to go back. I have
to go back and read that again. It was
not my intention to
>> I just think that we need to be really
clear. I also had an email today
thanking us for approving the indoor and
outdoor pool at Johnson pool. And I was
like, I just want to let you know we're
only doing an outdoor pool at this
point, but you know, and they were like,
well, we I thought it was both. And I
was like, no. So,
>> be nice.
>> If we have money,
>> Mr. President.
Um,
can you please somebody help me
understand what 30% means? Because I I
think that I'm not clear on well, we
keep talking about 30% or 60% or 100%.
And the second thing is I think it's
really really important that if we're
going to do this, it's accompanied with
a very specific and wellthoughtout
communications plan
>> so that some of these things don't
become you know
telephone game of well I heard I heard I
heard. Um, I I think it's really
important that we do a very specific
mar, you know,
what do I want to say? Concise marketing
plan about exactly what we're doing
before we start and then as we go along.
>> Yeah, Mr. President, we have a
facilitator here. We have a goal setting
meeting. The Reed Avenue project is a
very complicated undertaking which to
which lots of people in this room have
devoted lots of time and we're not going
to solve it tonight. And if there are
specific questions about it, then we
ought to get the people who have the
answers here in front of us, but not
tonight.
>> Well, why not,
>> Mr. President? Part of this is your
previous goals. We haven't was
definitely previous goal,
>> right? Well, we don't need a facilitator
then to do that. Mr. President, you
might just, you know, I
>> Okay. Well, we are we are trying to
review all goals.
Let's try to get Dr. answer. Mr. Labour,
you're you're leading that committee.
>> Mr.
>> Yes, I am. And it is very confusing and
a lot of information. We need to really
bring that together and really explain
not only to each other and to the other
people but to the people that are there
what that means because we don't really
get into railroad policy but their
acceptance of this 30% design which we
all are familiar with at least in
general with other projects. you have 30
60 90 and so but in this case it means a
little bit differently but it is not um
it means that they're finally discussing
with us the specifics and they there is
correspondence there and Mr. Cobb uh had
a hard time last night going through it
all because it had a lot of different
pieces and a lot of paths that uh maybe
some of us remember and maybe we don't.
But it uh I think that we can come up
with a uh and I think it's really
basically my responsibility as chairman
of the steering committee to uh come up
with a a report of where we came from
and where we're going and detail some of
these things. And I look forward to uh
working on that this weekend. Um, I know
that we have a lot of people that we
worked with and uh now um uh director
cop really didn't want to
um
have me doing any unauthorized
uh communication. So he communicated to
the consultants that they were to visit
with me and we we can come up with some
uh information here and that I think can
satisfy people. It is it is very
confusing that uh grant process it and
exactly what's involved and uh the whole
project itself is very very unique. So
uh I look forward to doing that. Um, I
think we can I can get you some good
information uh by next week and we can
review that. But, um, really this is the
point
for all this time. And I'm sure you
recall when I was appointed the chairman
of the steering committee,
I didn't have anything to report. It was
the same story.
We're trying to talk to the railroad.
We've got better people doing it. uh we
we had it but there was no communication
there where we brought forward a plan
and said this is what we want and they
came back and said this is what we must
have and then we go from there and I
think that uh the communication I have
with people um they've been incredibly
patient over there and understanding and
there are some good things happening and
we just need to
understand it a little better. I think I
could certainly do that myself, but I
can have a report by next week that uh
people can ask about and then we can
refer from that to other things. But
that's really the point is Tom didn't
want me uh talking to the consultants
and
making statements and I I really look
forward to going through that
correspondence. There's a lot of
correspondence there and it has specific
details. So, I I'll get that to you next
week. And I think that was a a point of
a goal, a worthy goal that uh
circumstances
brought in and the continuing effort of
of Tom Cobb brought this forward. So I
feel like that's a big progress towards
that goal and I can eventually see the
accomplishment of it. Thank you Mr.
Chairman Dr. Evans. Maybe um you know
30% when you start a plan and you you
draw it on paper and it 30% is kind like
it the 30,000 foot it kind of shows you
the alignment and some of the amenities
and info that conceptual conceptual then
as we get through it go to 65% they
start putting more and more detail and
then at the end it's all construction
ready to build and so basically what
we've done is we've shown them kind of
the conceptual what we want to do put it
on paper you know this is this we're
going to use the east half of the
railroad line we want to do this we want
to put these kind of amenities in there
and they looked at that said we think we
can live with that.
>> Um and so once we get approval then
we'll we'll finish the uh the final
design work
>> 30. Yeah. So at 30% if you get feedback
from the railroad said no that doesn't
work with us
>> can still be refined and changed and
gets a little more concrete by 60% and
by 90% it's pretty much ready.
>> You need to do all the work and you have
it ready to go and then have to change
something. So it's just kind of a
process. Everything's
>> Does that help?
>> It does.
>> Mr. President
>> the other part that I had in there and a
little bit of discussion on it last
night was the meat lumber triangle
and we have about 2.2 2 million
and if there's a way for us to leverage
some of that money with cultural trust
fund grants. I know you talked about a
business council um match which kind of
started to go down the
>> that died.
U we don't have to wait for the railroad
to work on that part of the read avenue
corridor.
I don't think we have $2.2 million. If
you got to take 900,000 off the top of
that,
>> right, cuz the match
>> for the grant match.
>> So, you're down to $1.2 million. And
honestly, I don't know what you can do
in that triangle
other than maybe
>> Well, plus he said we had to get some
plans redone. So, last night he said
that.
>> So, that was going to cost some money,
too.
>> So, I I think we have less than a
million dollars out of the original. I
mean, that's that's just my
understanding.
I'm
president.
One of the things I'm thinking is that
he mentioned last night the
>> Well, give me one second.
>> Well, this is so ill illustrative of the
point I made 10 minutes ago, which is
that
>> we we are reviewing last year's goals
and we're talking about
>> Okay. But but we have a memo from Tom.
The memor is if you understand this
project is a very carefully worded that
tells us some things but not everything
because that's the nature of Tom who is
a wonderful wonderful leader. But I
guess I I it just seems like it's not an
efficient use of our time, Mr. president
to spend trying to parse the details of
it because truly the only decision that
we really should set as a goal, which is
something I've said in my emails to you,
is are we going to identify a certain
amount of reserves
to keep this project moving forward?
>> Those are new goals. We are reviewing
old goals. We're trying to catch
everybody up. We all We all have a
project we worked on and we're trying to
review those.
>> Okay. Okay. But how? Well, fine. But but
Councilman Esco's goes exactly to this
point, which is there is a bunch of
complexity associated with developing
that triangle, including views that the
mayor has about it and that other people
on this council may have about it and
Mr. Ka. And are we going to parse
through all of those as well? because
I've sat through all those meetings and
I've heard all that discussion. You want
to know the details of them, then fine.
But we got all nine of us together.
We've spent the entire week together and
um if we want to talk about
>> Dr.
I can appreciate what you're saying,
Councilman Wolf. One of my I think one
of the challenges is is that it is not
very often that we're able to get
together and actually have discussions.
When we have a work session, something's
being presented and we can ask questions
about that work session. When we have a
council meeting, we have an agenda, but
there's not the opportunity for people
to ask what does 30% mean? I mean
there's we just don't get the to have
the robust conversation around these
projects as a group of nine, right? I
mean it's always happening in twos and
threes which I think ends up being that
telephone game that Councilman Emmens
referred to. So, while I think that it
may not feel like the best use of our
time, at least it allows us to
brainstorm, if you will, in the public
arena, which we have to do once we have
a quorum, um, and work through these
topics. Um, so that's I I did have a a
question or a comment and this may be
something that we want to think about
pursuing as far as funding for the
parker. And I think there was something
said about the bell a bell tower last
night is that um historic Cheyenne does
have some funding. Um and I think that
there are some other the cultural trust
and some different aspects that we might
be able to pursue and now that we have a
new grant writer on board as well that
um there may be some opportunities that
would help to and maybe some community
service organizations that would help
with that part. But I think that that's
I think you're you're right in my in my
opinion you're right that we have some
money. It probably isn't a lot that
might get us started on that part.
>> Thank you.
>> And I would like just like to say I am
adamantly opposed to committing any
reserves at this point until after March
9th until we know what we're going to
have to live with. um based on the
legislature and their activity.
>> We may not know what we have to live
with until after the election next fall.
Also,
>> well, at least we'll know about property
tax for the most part
and whether we're going to have a
dedicated direct distribution.
>> We will know that. We'll know that
amount.
They've agreed to a percentage at this
point.
>> Oh, we've agreed or the WHAM has agreed.
GAC agreed
>> and they also agreed to cut a a whole
agency. And so I think there's going to
be a lot of I think there's still room
for a lot of change in a 28 day session.
>> There is. But then we're still looking
at an election to change the
constitution in November that will
remove all property tax.
>> There's a lot going on.
>> Yeah, it's ever changing.
>> Okay. Um
Mr. President that's finally
frustration is you know government just
moves so slow projects that public hears
us talking about but they don't see
action on
is frustrating to me it's frustrating to
them
>> so I just want to see some dirt
concrete
something done
and using the money we have and leverage
it and get something accomplished. Even
if it's paving it,
whatever. I want to see something done.
When we get to the new goals section, we
we can talk about that and try to craft
the language if everybody agrees to it.
>> That's right.
>> All right. Let's um I would like to talk
to the revenue committee. Everybody got
their report. Is there anything you
would like to discuss or understand?
from the revenue committee.
>> Anyone?
>> I think we Mr. Chairman, Mr. President,
I think we've started off with um some
good action. It's definitely not um
we're not done. So, I think we've
definitely made some progress of things
that we're going to work on. So, I would
see these as being goals that we would
want to continue going forward.
Yeah. Yeah, I would agree with um Dr.
Emmens. I And I think that really goes
to her goal that she is listed on this
paper that what we're finding is is that
over time things have happened like um
there's no one set place in city
government for every lease that the city
is involved in. whether it's revenue
generating or um money that we're paying
out, there's no one repository
um for all leases. Um so we're doing a
lot of going from department to
department to department to collect
things. Um same with the fees. The only
way that we found an entire list of fees
was that um
Michael Skinner was able to pull up what
he had pulled together for me for open
gov um for the website to be able to
tell us and that's that listing has been
really helpful to be able to tell us
when the last time a fee was increased
what the recommend what the amount is
now and what the recommended amount is
if we were to bring it up to um current
dollars. So, what we're finding is that
there are just a lot of
systems lacking um that like just even
having an inventory of all the
properties that we own and um whether
they're where they're at as far as being
able to um be used or not used or
whether there's major utilities going
through. A lot of that is in Tom Cobb's
head and I think Tom is online tonight.
And I think that, you know, if he were
to, you know, have a traumatic brain
injury, god forbid, or retire, we would
be so screwed. Win the lottery. Yeah. We
would be so screwed. So, I just think we
need to have in order for succession to
happen because people do turn over, we
need to really work on systems, which
we'll talk about under new goals.
>> Okay, great. Any other questions for
that committee?
Okay. um safety team your your report I
think as I read it you felt like you
were pretty well done with it.
>> Yes sir. And I Mr. President and I just
want to thank my colleagues Mr. Moody
and Mr. Leborn for all the hard work. Um
we had consistent meetings with Cheyenne
police over the course of the year. Um
kudos go to all of all of the governing
body as well. If you'll recall, um we
had increased $100,000 for increased uh
traffic enforcement. Um we we um
approved their uh funding request for
their urban SDK software which allows
them to allocate their resources to
where they are most needed for speed
enforcement
uh using using data. Um the creation and
implementation mayor of the critical saf
safety team has been applauded I think
by everybody in the community at least
those folks that I've talked to. Uh we
passed the noise ordinance approved the
bid for the thermoplastic for crosswalks
and then the no approved the safe
streets for all measure. So we feel we
completed that goal. Um we did have a
couple of recommendations. Uh there's
very good momentum on this issue. Uh one
thing that an obstacle that we ran into
was um we discovered through uh city
attorney Brody that uh we cannot just
make changes um to local speed limits
that uh comes through the state
legislature.
>> Yeah, it's you guys didn't know that.
>> Yeah. Well, we we tried to do an ender
round and I guess there has been a
Supreme Court.
>> We'd already tried an end years ago.
>> Yeah, I was on council that I must have
forgotten conveniently. Um, so
>> years ago we made residential streets 25
miles per hour,
>> right?
>> And then we were told that state statute
says it's going to be 30,
>> right? So, we we didn't know if it would
be worth it to uh I know this year's a
budget session, but perhaps ask Wham if
if that's something that they can carry
forward to uh in their efforts with the
legislature to allow more local control
over something like that. Uh we
certainly and and Mr. Moody and I will
have more discussion on this under new
goals, but we certainly recognize the
value and importance of crosswalks,
particularly in neighborhoods, parks,
and schools. We all know that we've seen
several um very regrettable tragedies
uh with young people in our community
and um and fatalities due to um due to
inadequate resources and also distracted
driving. And so anything that we can do
to prevent that or any measures we can
take we feel that we should.
And then uh the last thing uh the level
of bureaucracy is to implement signage
and crosswalks in neighborhoods
>> um is is mad is maddening quite
honestly. Um, I'm thinking the crosswalk
at 8th Avenue and Kerry, uh, 8th Avenue,
which can still be, despite our
increased traffic safety, 8th Avenue can
be, uh, the Indianapolis Speedway at
times. Um, Tom's been great to work with
and so has Mr. Aemon. Um, but
I'm of the opinion at what point do we
measure engineer warrants and common
sense in neighborhoods? We still don't
have, do we?
>> When we talk about the drag racing,
>> we talk about the information about
potential drag including drag racing uh
penalties for the state.
>> Oh, yeah. Go ahead.
>> Yeah, thank you. Uh, Mr. President. Um,
we also talked about there needs to be
higher penalties for drag racing. Uh, I
would say it is a problem not just here
in Cheyenne. I was in Sheridan over the
summer. It was it's a problem there too.
Even a problem in Casper. It was even a
problem near South Pass City. There were
two motorcycles that were playing
chicken there near the Oregon Trail. Um,
so I think that this is probably gonna
have to be an interim topic with the
judiciary committee. There needs to be
higher penalties. Right now it's only
$100. It probably has been updated since
I think the 60s. So, we need to be I was
thinking, you know, first time offense,
you know, $500, but then third time it's
got to be an automatic felony because
you're purposely taking people's lives
in there. A lot of states have
implemented to where a third time it's
three strikes, you're out felony charge.
So,
>> without the estate, that's a state that
we can do that,
>> right?
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> We do have Dr. Aldish. She has a
question.
>> I'm just wondering if we might want to
start a list of WHAM resolutions. Um, so
because every spring we get to they send
out a thing and say, "Hey, send us your
resolutions." And we're like, uh, you
know, gosh, Richard Johnson, I think, is
was like the resolution king there. So,
but, um, maybe the resolution about
changing the residential speed limits
and things, um, it might be something
that we could do a resolution on for
Wham and Wham could decide whether
that's going to be on their legislative
agenda.
>> I know it's progress is slow, but
>> Mr. Way to do it. May I address that?
>> Yes, please.
>> That discussion reminded me I need to
send out an email to our region, but I'm
glad you brought it up. Wham has changed
the
because of the way the the um
legislature works as I sat after the
legislature last year. I sat there and
they were already determining interim
topics and we weren't going to have our
annual meet and this was in March and we
weren't going to have our annual meeting
till June which meant we were three
months behind behind the curve. So in my
urging we've changed the schedule um we
will be asked to come up with our
suggestions for interim topics at the
meeting in February. Oh,
>> do we need to actually do it resolution
format or or is there going to be a way
to just submit it without having to go
through the process?
>> I think the discussion I will try and
find that out. I think the discussion
will be um during the regional meetings
>> and does it still have I'm sorry.
>> Does it still have to be voted on by the
council before it can go forward to when
>> do you know? It's not how I remember.
>> No.
>> No. And no. I I honestly I think that's
part of the purpose of the regional
meeting is to come up with
>> a list.
>> In the past has generally been elect the
representative and get a report. This
time we're wanting to have actual
proposals in topics come out of the
region meeting.
>> Okay.
>> So I think our member of the discussion
will vote on those during the during the
regional meetings and then they'll be
taken on to the board and then the board
will take them on to the LLC. But it
won't require that the council has to
vote on a resolution before it can go to
WH.
>> It's not coming from us. Now it's coming
out of the region.
>> Okay. That used to be a thing, right?
That we have to approve it. Yeah.
>> Yeah. We were supposed to approve and
send them on. Thank you. Any other
questions for the Mr. President? You
know, one time we were talking about
that issue of drag racing and we were
thinking outside the box where was a
place we could give
kids a
somewhere to go to actually do that
>> instead of doing it on the city streets.
And
>> yeah,
>> that never really materialized. I know
that Julesburg, Colorado has a place
that they
>> fabulous.
>> They let them go out there every
Saturday night from
6:00 to 10 and do their thing and then
they get it out of their system and
>> we got give them a runway at the
airport.
>> I was going to say some communities are
doing that.
I think it is
dangerous.
>> That's what it is.
>> It's worth it's worth further
consideration.
Thank you.
Um
I meant at the beginning of the meeting
I meant to say as soon as the board of
adjustments is done next door we'll open
this and if we get some more air flow
through here they should be done the
next few minutes.
>> I just think that was really nice.
>> You like the heat?
>> I do.
>> Oh my lord. And our last the last item I
have anyway for old businesses is the
Belvore Ranch. Um, and I'm going to talk
more about that under new business, but
u we have a lot of progress going on
there. It's been a very good year. Um,
we're I believe we will have at least
one and possibly two proposals in front
of you in the next 30 to 60 days. Um,
one is a solar array, the other is a
natural gas fire data center type of
complex.
Uh we're working with a Wyoming company
that builds natural gas
power and uh they have identified
five parcels on the ranch totaling about
1300 acres that is primed for for a data
center.
So the uh
we've got the proposal from them. with
with the lawyer. I guess uh taking a
look at the language uh would be the
potential for both a um
property sale or lease to the centers as
well as a percentage of the gross
profits off the power plant. So it could
be a very nice revenue stream.
Um the firm looking at the solar is um
is a foreign company but they're in 40
different countries it's a massive
company and uh the way they they would
include us would be through royalties I
believe is the term they used as a as a
rather than just leasing the land
royalties off the gross profit of the so
anyway been a good year and we'll
discuss that more hopefully if Mr.
President.
>> Yes.
>> And how are they going to access this to
construct and manage those facilities?
>> Exit 345
on the interstate right across from the
truck stop. The rest area
that the ranch is right there.
>> Can't wait to see the plans.
>> Yeah. So, um it's looking it's looking
good. We can talk more if you want to
continue that as goal. any any other
discussion on old goals that you want to
talk about for I'm Dr. Stuts do the you
kind of quoted us on the new goals I'm
just talking too much so any other old
goal discussion
>> not old goals
well I wanted to ask I think we're
almost done or we will be finished
quickly on annexation correct
>> yes
>> I think we're like in the last parcel of
annexation
>> yes Dr. I can't remember if it's one
left or one in a in a small one.
>> Um we're almost done
>> because that one of the goals we set six
years ago was annexation. The storm
utility fee we set six years ago which
um I'd have to say I was a little
surprised when I was in Europe to find
out it was being delayed election was
being delayed till April. Um
do are we and then now I've heard that
it might even be after the November
election. So, is anybody can we have an
update on that since that was one of our
goals?
>> The reason for the delay, if I may, Mr.
President, go ahead.
>> Was that Board of Public Utilities is
having it's taken them significantly
longer than they thought it would to
figure out some of the billing. I'm a
really good example. I on my office
I own the property but I have two lees
and the bill should go to the
the storm water utility bills supposed
to go to the land owner the water bill
is currently going to the lees. So, in
an instance like that with with
rental properties or especially with
commercial, they it's taking them longer
to track down who the bill should go to.
And I'm the other part of the example is
I own a piece of vacant property with
two other people.
um it's undeveloped
yet we should get a storm water bill
but because it's undeveloped we're not
getting a water bill. So then they have
to track down that ownership. So that's
just taken longer than than they thought
it would. Um, initially I'd heard April.
I'd heard as late as July. And if it's
going to be with April, I'm a little
concerned, but with July, I really think
if that's the case, I told my opinion is
I told the mayor, I think we should
postpone it until after the 25th and
sixth pity elections and just delay it
till next January. Um,
so that's something we need to be
considering. Well, I and I think it's
something we need to have serious
conversations about because I know that
in talking with Mr. F day that uh he's
been in conversation with the school
district and has just cut their stom
utility fee by like $60,000
because of some changes that were made
in how it's being calculated. So the
longer this goes,
the more
challenging it becomes, I think, to
implement.
>> True. And the other thing that
complicates it is that Senator Crumb has
a bill in the legislature that
>> right
>> will dramatically affect us.
>> Okay.
>> Any anything else under I I didn't
realize that was a
2025. I thought that was an earlier
goal. He was
>> It was But we were talking about old
goals. And that's one of my frustrations
and why I didn't turn any new goals in
for tonight was because we never seem to
wrap up something. We I just feel like
we have all these loose ends out there
and we never can actually like check it
off the list
>> and put it away.
>> Got thirst.
>> I was going to say I got mine done. That
was six penny. We finished that last
night.
If I could just circle back to the storm
water fee. Um, today Wham met with the
uh chairman of the select water
committee and um he asked if it would be
possible that we would postpone
implementing a fee and then they would
do an interim study on it and try to see
if they could work out um a compromise
of how we would move forward with the
thing. If not, um that bill would move
forward and potentially uh restrict our
ability to uh to do the speak because
right now the the uh
the bill that Senator Chrome just has
written says you cannot do these things
and you already have one and within a
certain period of time you have to have
a municipal election to ratify it. Um,
and so what Senator Bonner had had uh
had asked would be if we'd be willing to
sit back and not collect our the let it
be an interim study and then they would
try to come up with a with a compromise
language that would allow us to move
forward. Um, and so I don't know how
people feel about that, but that was uh
that was I was on the phone as you guys
walked in from them asking us how we
would feel about that. You know, I told
him I was going to see you guys. I'd ask
that question. Maybe we can talk about
it later, but that's uh that was his way
of trying to to to pull that back just a
little bit. Let let us calm down and
figure out a way to uh manage that so we
might be able to still successfully
collect a fee and and work on storm
water.
>> Any other
old projects from any year you would
like to talk about?
Russell Leworp.
>> Well, as the champion of the pump house,
I'm very pleased that we are now uh
closer to uh what has always been the
problem, which is the uh continued use
of the building. So, um I guess that
speaks to the ups and downs and rounds
and rounds of these issues. And uh but I
I did want to note that
um
a lot of money got spent, a lot of time
passed, but it was a very difficult
issue and I think we can look at it more
comprehensively now. The path, the
wetland,
the building itself and uh so sometimes
it's it's very difficult to get that
resolution.
But I I
uh definitely think we could have done
better with the uh or I could have done
better with how how it went along.
But sometime, frankly, I think
everything we talked about tonight and
all the legislative portions and the
storm water, all of these things mean
we're in a good position with the
funding we have in the reserves, but we
got to be careful and really think about
how we're going to do this. And so, um,
that's my thoughts on the pump house.
We have one more question. Dr.
>> Um I think going back to Dr. Emman's
point about telephone. Um I know that we
have two people, the mayor I'm guessing
and Mark who will be going to the six
penny meeting next Wednesday. Is that
>> Thursday?
>> Next Thursday. Um I think it would be
really helpful if when those things
occur if that not that I think everybody
will want to attend or anybody might
want to attend but just that we know
that those are happening so that if
people are interested and want to attend
recognizing that we would not some of us
I mean if you're not one of the
designated people you're not going to
have a vote and not necessarily even a
voice but to be able to watch the
process. So um where will the meeting be
held and at what time? I'm guessing it's
a public meeting.
>> Yes. Well, it doesn't have to be because
you don't have a forum from anybody
there, but I will find out before we
leave.
>> Archer,
>> but I'm assuming it's at Archer.
>> Well, the dinner is at Archer, but we
have the meeting most of which
will give you an answer.
>> Anything else?
Okay, here's the fun part. Let's talk
about new projects or completing some
that we're still working on.
Melissa, help us take over.
>> And so, um, Mr. President, if I may, the
your previous goals, you're going to
continue to explore new revenue streams
and your goal is completed. Yes, Mr.
Moody. Yes, we're right gentlemen.
>> And you identified um last night.
>> Yes.
>> Um and and so if if I if I may, while I
have you all, I I just want to say thank
you for the work that you do. It to to
be a a public servant is is something to
um be astounded at. uh your your work
influences safety and the opportunity
and belonging and quality of life for
tens of thousands of people here in
Cheyenne. And thank you for taking the
time to do that. Um in front of you, you
do you have you have this
little chart here which is a it's a bit
of a breakdown of the goals that you
presented to to Jennifer. And thank you
to Jennifer. I don't think anything can
happen without Jenny.
And and so I'm hoping we can
>> go through go through these. Maybe when
we open the door, we can put some things
on the wall, but right now we're
squished.
>> But if we can look at this and go
through one at a time and and really
talk about what is it that that you're
trying to accomplish and and be specific
with what the council's role is. We want
to talk about metrics and we want to
talk about champions. And so we
finalized the six penny. Your your goal
is met. But but your plan to educate and
the public, um I I'd like you to talk
about that a little bit more and and see
how we if we need to turn that into a
goal and is that the same as Dr. Renie's
goal of discussing and implementing a
public information strategy?
>> Sure. Um,
I think that this is going to be a
challenging tax environment um, in our
community and with the folks that um,
would be our our wouldbe voters. So, I
think it's going to be really really
important that we educate the public
about Fitbits Penny. um back in the day
and this is the benefit of being old is
that sometimes you remember how things
that used to get done and used to be
when there was a road construction
project there'd be a and I've shared
this with the mayor there'd be a great
big sign that said your fifth penny at
work right or your sixth penny at work
um or your one cent sales tax at work
and some at some point we got away from
that it even used to be on the back of
the police cars that we purchased with
fifth penny sales tax money um so the
mayor and I had that conversation
And um I think that that has been
something that department heads have
become aware of. Um I know that with the
rebranding we we're seeing the new brand
on uh city vehicles. I'm hoping that as
we're purchasing new items were, you
know, tagging them, not necessarily like
an inventory tag, but a tag that just
says, especially if it was bought with
fifth or sixth penny sales tax money,
that lets the public know so that they
can see their dollars at work. um
because I think we we don't do a really
good job of letting people know um
visually what those funding streams are.
So, I'm hoping that um I also thought
that um I think I visited with Mr. about
this last night. um our director
Nimichek talked about um our need for a
new building and I thought that really
she should probably put together a
PowerPoint and she should be our dog and
pony show for all the community
organizations on why we need a new
building because um she can she really I
think was able to give people
examples and help paint a picture of why
we need a new building. when they walk
in the front door, they don't see, you
know, necessarily that um, you know, the
heating and ventilation system is so
old, they don't see that we only have
one out of two elevators working unless
they physically come into the building
to touch the human resource department.
And I think um, you know, the ADA
conversation is huge, that we need to
have accessibility for all of our
citizens, not just those that are able
body. And so I think that we need to
figure out um how we're going to for
lack of a better term sell the six penny
ballot to the community. um and if we
expect them to vote for it because quite
honestly there are people who are going
to vote no just because it's a tax and I
think unfortunately right now the
pendulum swings and that pendulum um has
swung where most
or many um may be of that ilk and I
think that we need to really um focus in
on I was glad to see that our six ballot
ended up being primarily
um
uh infrastructure and public safety
focused and I think that those sell and
uh with a constituent that u may not be
really responsive to more tax or new
tax.
>> You heard that last night
I would support those things.
>> So I heard you say two two different
things. One is educating the public with
what's on the sixth penny and why
and then educating the public with where
their dollars are being spent
>> or where they happen to to acknowledge
that.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> And we used to have that years ago on
police cars.
Yes.
>> I don't know why we got away from that.
>> Probably because it cost money on there,
right?
>> Summer during Kak's turn was cheap.
tell your story.
>> Yes.
>> Could could we maybe have just a a real
short discussion on what we've done in
the past as far as
presenting to the public. Um I know we
have some meetings set up already with
like Rotary and Kuanas where we can go
and do I just don't know what we've
really done in the past maybe
>> and what we're limited to. and what
we're limited to.
>> Well, you remember back in the cost
phase, we actually put together a big
committee and
>> yeah,
>> we did that. In fact, Mr. Labour and I
even debated once on um one of the
taxes. I don't remember which one it
was. It was a long time ago, but um
>> who won?
>> Well, it passed. So,
>> it passed. So I guess I
valid items and
um their purpose
>> and maybe Patty Reeseland from the
mayor's council for people with
disabilities and that group would be
willing to help advocate for an ADA
accessible city
Well, I've always been concerned through
many of these cycles with exactly what
is information and what is advocacy.
And I think at times we've um
blurred that line. And I think that uh
from my perspective after what I've been
seeing next door here lately uh we
better be darn careful about it. But
truly I believe that the point that was
just made I believe that that uh the
airline group had their own political
action committee.
>> Yes.
>> The um the Greenway committ the Greenway
Foundation has had its own political
action committee.
I had a minor political action committee
for the last ballot for the downtown
issue. I think we need to really go to
the people that have the money that
understand and say we need a real strong
advocacy coming from a political option
committee. not from not from not from
saying this is what's on the ballot and
conceivably also why we need it, but I'm
thinking back and I've been through this
from the very initiation of of what was
the capital facilities tax. We've got an
incredible story to tell here of what
that penny has accomplished.
And that story might some of us might
remember
and certainly those like myself are very
much in favor of it. But these other
people, do they know where that went? Do
they know what it went for? And do they
know that that is a tool in the state of
Wyoming that is very powerful and that
to my knowledge unique? You know, it is
really it's voter approved. But I think
that you have to tell that story in
detail and and you have to advocate for
it. And to do that, you got to and
certainly those of us that are
interested in that can be members of
that political action committee. It's
perfectly legal and go out and you know
I I want to go to the fire union and I
want to say fellas,
what can you do here? They are a
political group of people and they
advocate for projects.
>> I've done that.
>> And what did they tell you?
>> They're all over it.
>> Good. But but I mean those are the kinds
of people that that certainly the
chamber uh certainly you know when we go
to uh Kowanas which I understand not
Kowanas Rotary excuse me uh soon I think
it's not out of line to say there's
somebody in the back of the room here
that you can talk to about advocacy
>> and and really push that because
I feel like
the understanding of that is
critical and and when we start talking
about these projects I feel like if
we're talking about the rehabilitation
of this building which this discussion
has pointed out it doesn't look bad you
know but the detail needs to come into
it well then you start talking about the
public safety center that was a building
that was rehabilitated.
You start talking about the uh library,
the botanic gardens, and all of the
infrastructure. And certainly, very
importantly, and I think this is part of
why we've been so successful over the
years, we've kept those rural
communities alive and they're thriving.
And we need to talk about their their
waterline. and we need to talk about why
we are one county that works together on
this process. So I'm way way interested
in advocacy direct vote for this is why
and then of course on the other hand the
city itself and our public information
can say this is what it is but we got to
provide this is why. So, I really look
forward to doing that because
um
I think that the whole question of the
storm water fee
and what what we're talking about here,
um I've pushed for that for 30 years.
Perhaps it would be prudent to wait, but
that's a decision we're going to have to
make. And so
as far as I understand it, and someone
could correct me if I'm wrong, I don't
believe we've ever had the sixth and the
fifth in the same cycle.
>> We're launching.
>> We have no launching.
>> Oh, this is anemic. That's what I
thought.
>> It's a perfect storm in a bad time.
>> Yep. So, so whatever advocacy you have
for the sixth immediately ties into the
advocacy for the fifth
and that's where those interest groups
and certainly
I don't think I could uh campaign in
this building with the employees
but I think we know who they are and
they should be in the game. They live
here. They have families. They have
friends. And
if we lost the sixth and the fifth,
uh,
>> would
Mr. Labour.
>> Yep. So I, you know, I I believe we need
to step up
stronger advocacy from those of us that
believe in that and really go out and
ask some of those banks,
some of those uh
I'm I'm not sure. I' I've never really
approached them, but uh certainly the uh
big corporate
Microsoft people, you know, I don't know
if they can participate in that, but we
should have a really strong
balanced,
social media, press, television, the
whole
campaign. Because if we lose,
and I want to emphasize this, I've lost
And if we lose this, you'll have an
experience that you won't even believe.
And then who are we going to fire? So,
as of today, I'm saying strong advocacy.
And anybody that wants to work with me
on that, I'm glad to. But we see where
we've had success
and where others have had success.
So
people need to be reminded and they need
to think about it. So that's that's
really my point.
>> So if you have a plan that spells out
where you're going to advocate and what
you're going to do, who creates this
plan,
>> whoever wants to work on it.
>> Well,
I think we need to back up for a second.
We need to, in my opinion, we need to
have somebody who understands marketing.
We need to have somebody who knows what
they're doing. We can't just slap
together something because we have to
have a good framework that really
identifies the critical pieces to a
marketing plan because there's different
stages in this. One is building the
plan, one is executing the plan and
building out and you know getting people
excited and things like that. Those are
two different skill sets. Are we able to
use city resources to do this
>> for education?
>> I mean not
>> for education. So we can use our public
information officer to build a
educational campaign and a marketing
campaign to educate.
>> Yeah. as long as it doesn't advocate.
>> Well, I mean, we're pay we're paying
people to do these things and they're
the professionals.
>> So, but I do think it would be good to
have
You're getting volunteered, you know.
>> Um well, Mr. Mayor, will you volunteer?
>> Um I do think it would be good to have a
couple people from this body working
with with them to build a plan.
>> I think that's a great idea. I don't
think we can disable real build this
that's too
>> I I did want to mention uh President
Cclair that uh Mr. Labboard and I had a
conversation that I think that something
that might be really impactful and
effective and would be free would be to
have um some of our colleagues from Pine
Bluffs and Burns and Alban and um
different uh entities that have
benefited from the fifth or six penny
sales tax ballots uh come and speak to
us under public comments to give a
little testimony about, you know, what
does it mean to Burns that they were
able to um I don't even remember it was
it new water lines or um and also all of
their new lots out there their 62 lots
um or Pine Bluffs where they were able
to do their um kind of their industrial
area and
>> yeah subdivision Alban with their
trailer park you know I just I think
because we have the majority of the
voters in our in Cheyenne city limits
and I think that um Mr. Mr. Labour made
a really good point that we need to show
a a concerted front and encourage
support of all those things and then
maybe in turn, you know, uh we'll have
the opportunity um somebody from this
council, the president or um someone to
visit their council meetings and um give
public comment at the end of the
meeting, you know, about why the six
penny or penny is important to the city
of Cheyenne. I just think those are some
while we may not have a lot of people
sitting in the audience. Um, and we only
I don't know how many we get Jennifer on
a Monday night to watch. It's I know
it's usually kind of a handful, right?
Like it can you tell?
>> I mean, it it it does depend. I mean,
Facebook has a pretty good um following,
you know, and then we can see afterward.
I think that Matt probably can see how
many were on Facebook and, you know, we
can see how many are on YouTube and how
many have those videos.
>> I know that usually by the time I've hit
the my car has hit 19th Street, my phone
is ringing off the hook to talk about
what happened at the council meeting
from people that have been watching.
They need to get alive because you're
sitting at home watching council
meetings on Monday nights. It's not
>> you need concerned with what happens
within our city.
>> We need citizens. There there's one
other I think really important piece to
this is that I think it's important for
us as a body to make sure that we are
all committed to staying together on
this process that we've identified those
11 things
and I always think of it as do no harm
that there's no one of us that's going
to speak
against
any of the um ballot initiatives.
I to me that's real important because
that'll sink us also real quickly.
people.
>> So I I think we just need to know is
there anybody who is not going to be
able to in good conscious or you know
with their principles or ideals is there
anything people are not going to be
comfortable supporting?
>> I will tell you there isn't has anything
to do with 15th Street other than curb
and gutter and sidewalks. Um, anything
that has to do with the rail cars that
um are being painted to be put down
there, I will not.
>> Well, we already said that.
>> No, but I know I mean when that wording
comes out, if there is anything that
alludes to that,
>> I'm a no-go. So,
>> but with the things that we identified
last night, is there anybody Mark, are
you on board with everything?
>> I need to look the final resolution
first.
>> We discussed it at length last night.
Yeah, just let me see the final
resolution.
>> So, of the 11 things that we talked
about last night, is there anything
you're not comfortable with?
>> Again, I need resolution. Most things
I'm okay with.
>> The other thing that goes with that, you
guys, if we made an agreement among all
by the our governing bodies that we will
not talk about in other cities or towns
or counties projects except positively,
um that they won't question our projects
and we won't question their projects.
And so we made that commitment many many
years ago and I think it's helped us as
a county by being positive about things
>> and and if you can't be positive just
don't say anything
>> you know it's
>> mommy used to say that
>> it's that do no harm I don't have to
maybe like what you say but that doesn't
mean I'm going to go out and say I don't
like what you say you know I just think
that's real clear
>> united front as a council is it is is
important
We got a list of the county's projects
and then
>> Wednesday we get them uh next Thursday,
excuse me.
>> Look forward to that.
>> And then remember, Mr. Leward, what'll
happen is uh we'll put the ballot
together and it'll include everybody's
projects and then I'll come back to our
governing body for approval.
>> Right.
>> We'll get a chance to see everybody's
projects,
>> right? Well, I think uh certainly uh
from my point of view, we voted last
night for this list
and
I
doubt I would we couldn't possibly
oppose the counties, but that's really
not our call. But certainly, I thought
that was a balanced good approach.
That's why I voted for it. And I think
that that's all you really need to refer
to is that it was almost unanimous and
we committed to uh that list of projects
and whatever and that would be something
that might be worth
consideration is there are other actions
and items and projects
outside of the ballot that are sure to
be difficult, but that's outside the
ballot. we're talking and keep it right
there to those projects and what we're
trying to do and there's plenty to talk
about and I think
most people could come to understand
yeah you're going to have controversy on
things but this was a a united choice
and I certainly
>> feel like that you know that and I want
to be united with whatever those rural
places want. So, can we agree that if we
don't support something, we don't say
something?
>> Can you do that? Are you okay?
>> Yeah. I mean, I'm going to provoke the
rows got to get done. I think everybody
agrees on that.
>> But the ballot's not going to change
from what we did last night to Tuesday
when we voted.
>> I just want to make sure it's not going
to change. That's my biggest thing
because I know it happened in uh sitting
in Colorado then.
>> Yeah. here. So, what is the
because you were a no vote last night,
correct?
>> Okay. You were. Yes. Okay. So, is there
>> was the only right vote last night.
>> Is there any is there anything that's
giving you pause, but you're like,
>> I just want might make my amendment
range of the roads. That's the only
thing.
>> We're done.
>> Oh, I thought we're not doing it through
the whole council.
>> Yeah, he's right. I mean, it could get
me it could get amended in council on
Tuesday, but the likelihood is pretty
slim.
>> Yeah, that's why
>> I mean, every amendment that got put up
last night pretty much got shot down
>> Tuesday in public finance.
>> It goes to It goes to council.
>> Goes to council.
Yeah. But
>> and then it's a week from now.
>> Okay. It's not this next week.
>> I just think we've had meetings. It
seems like a committee week. I'm sorry.
I screwed that up earlier.
>> Okay. Okay. So, no
meeting.
>> I was trying to figure out what
>> it's a week. No, it's a week.
>> Okay. I'm going to keep us going. Thank
you.
>> Okay.
>> Dr. Renie, is there anything else?
>> Yeah. My actually my subject on that, my
thoughts on that were totally different.
I mean, I agree.
>> Okay.
>> We need to do something on the sixth
penny, but in discussing implementing a
public information strategy, I am glad
that that Matt's here because I brought
this up a little bit last year. Um, and
mayor, you told me that that Matt was
working on making improvements on how we
contact people, but I don't know that,
you know, I know we did the branding,
the new branding, but I I look at issues
like um, one, I know that when Jennifer
sent out
the information for Council of Coffee
for both WS three and WS one, several of
those bounced back. So, I don't know
that we have a a current listing of
video outlets and I think that should be
updated. Um, but more importantly and
and Matt may not have time and we may
need to contract this or get or get him
some help, but I want to start,
you know, let me back up. Jeff and I
talked I talked to Jeff about this last
night and Jeff said, "Mark, we have we
have all of our work sessions, all of
our council meetings, everything's
online. People can find, you know,
people can learn stuff if they want."
They don't. Okay. Um,
a handful of people do, but generally
people don't pay attention to what we're
doing until they think it affects them.
So, I think we need to start spoon
feeding stories to the media, which
means we and getting out ahead of
things. Like on the storm water utility,
we probably should have had one or two
one lengthy article or or several short
ones explaining what our costs are, what
we're experiencing, why we're having to
do it. Um,
warrants. We probably should have had
articles a couple three months ago going
over giving examples of, you know, we
have issues of this. Um, mayor, you told
me last night about two incidences where
we were arrested,
one really heinous criminal because of
the flock cameras and having to
>> and now, but we're now I know we're
behind the we're behind the curve on
that again
and and just I mean those little
instances like the guy you told me to
raped the girl multiple times and we
caught him because of a flock camera
that I don't think that got posted on
the police department's website, but we
ought to be sending that out to the
media. all the all those little bits of
information when we do something good
needs to go out there and hit this stuff
off ahead of time and and I'm you know I
know it's kind of it should be our goal
but honestly mayor it comes back to you
and it comes back to Matt and so I don't
know if you need help or if we need to
contract with
>> journalism students at the wingspan to
say hey we need this article written
tomorrow and pay them by the piece
But she wanted to do something different
from than what we've been doing.
>> The little gal that we had last summer
that did the social media post and
things.
>> She was great.
>> I thought she was amazing.
>> It was read it.
>> Actually, the little girl that helped
the high school girl. I was going to say
I actually did she I created a video
about the uh city council like when it
is and all that in the times. It's never
been posted though.
>> Yeah. I mean, she did create a lot of
content, but it hasn't hasn't been
>> Well, anyway, I want you guys thoughts
on that because I am tired of getting
beat up when we could have headed some
of this stuff out at the past.
>> Well, I'd like to know stuff before the
media knows like about the April delay.
>> I mean,
>> I didn't know.
>> Well, sometimes we're learning stuff
when the public learns it. So,
>> so I have a media person that works for
me, a um what do we call it?
Communication, outreach, and education.
and her whole job is to be on social
media. So, she's on Facebook, Instagram,
websites. Um, she does all of our like
at the movies we have a we advertise
there. Um, she does newspaper articles.
She works with the TV. She used to be
the TV manager. Um, she does our
newsletter that goes out all across the
community. I mean, that's her whole job
is she's developed a communication plan
for us that talks about how we do each
one of the media outlets or or
platforms. And we have a schedule built
that we know these are the things that
come out before we make any change on
anything like a vaccine. we frontload
it, you know, like three weeks before to
say this is a change so that people
start getting used to it before it
actually happens.
Um I mean and she does a great job. You
cannot have her. But um that's her whole
job is just to coordinate all of that
stuff. and our out our reach out into
the city and the county is like 30
40,000 people
>> and the fire department and and the
police department both have public
information officers. I mean they and
they've got six ballots. So maybe maybe
the three entities could work together
to develop this campaign and to educate.
But I agree, we need to have it needs to
be an ongoing every
>> day. It has to be shaping the narrative
on some of this stuff and especially big
things,
you know, and I know you can't always
predict it on, you know, on the
on the administrative warrants. We
probably should have seen that coming in
today's environment
>> at the top,
>> but we didn't.
>> Sure.
>> At the top, change policy strategy.
Doesn't the college have somebody that
we could
>> Well, like I said, I mean, they have the
wingspan on their newspaper and they
have students. We need
>> have amazing high school programs in our
city that do this.
>> So, I don't know if we just need to
contract that out or Well,
or if Matt needs another person or Matt
can I don't know what your schedule is,
Matt. So, I'm not presuming to tell you
you've got time to do this, but I just
want to bombard the media with stuff
that we're doing in advance and with and
like the two instances the Lord told me
about last night with the flat camera,
when we when good things happen,
>> nobody knows.
>> We need to we need to make sure we get
our backs patted. Let's
>> tell our story.
>> Isn't that the number one tool they use
when there's Amber Alerts?
>> I don't know. We only have 23 of them,
so
Okay. Want to keep us rolling? Any any
other clarification on that potential
goal?
Okay.
Dr. Emmens, I want to move on to yours
here. Implement a project management
process or system that can easily be act
accessed. I have a question about this.
Is that accessed by the council or by
the public?
>> Probably both.
But definitely by
>> internal and external.
>> Yeah, definitely internal. Um and the
reason that I thought about this is um
it seems like that we don't really know
where
we don't know what the progress is on
to that that issue that um Michelle
brought up. Um,
if we had a project management
software or a system
that's used throughout the city or at
least through with um your office, mayor
on those big projects that we're
involved in that had the project manager
regularly tracking those so that we
could actually see progress. So that
one, we don't have so many things just
hanging out because they probably
aren't, but we just don't know that.
There's probably huge amounts of
progress being made, but we don't know
that. Um,
so if we could see what the progress is,
where we're at at different points, and
that things are not being for whatever
reason
ne not neglected. I don't mean that
necessarily in a bad way, but you get
busy and you start doing one project and
maybe another one starts falling behind.
Um, so a project management software
that we would be able to see and track
projects
>> and they're not that expensive. We use
two on my team and my day job. A liquid
planner runs about 2500 a year and
Trello which actually only runs about
300 a year. Um, they're not expensive
and everybody can access them that you
give access to and track them. And we
have a project manager for the city that
maybe he's already using a project
management software and we just don't
know it. The the nice thing about him
too is then you can start identifying
where there is potential problems that
are delaying why things aren't getting
done. you know, maybe we can look at it
and say, "Okay, obviously we don't have
enough people working on this pro on
this project or we don't have the right
tools for them to get done what they
need to do or there's a policy that we
have that's standing in the way of their
accomplishment."
So, that that's what I was looking at
>> picturing like a dashboard.
>> Yeah.
>> Kind of. I think would would it be the
same that you see internally as what you
display to the public or
>> probably not a different page
>> does
>> but a dashboard would be great
>> what you talked about does that have the
capability of doing both
>> what I talked about is it it has a
dashboard and it has a project basically
well for lack of a better term card for
every single project and you can at any
time access it and see things tasks have
been assigned to different people and
you can see where they're at on their
task and It gives you a projected
timeline that works backwards. It gives
you it creates task list. It's um I
don't know what you guys use.
>> We use Trello all over why do it's
>> it's amazing. I use it at home.
>> E R E L L O.
>> Yeah,
>> they have a free version that I use at
home.
>> I'm probably somewhat brainwashed on
this because this is what my daughter
does professionally. She's the project
manager for a marketing firm in Denver.
And so all the projects that they do,
Katie Track or Yeah, she is the project
manager for all of them. Um, so I've
listened to her talk about it forever
and ever.
>> What did she use?
>> Um, some professional. Yeah, it's a
>> We've just moved to ClickUp is a new one
we're using.
>> Yeah, I can't remember what the name of
it is.
>> I Googled.
>> It's also what Dave Tar's business used
because that's where she started it. So,
but that's was mine. Okay.
How how would we I guess measure that?
How how would we know like once it's
implemented and working then the goals
achieved? Is that
>> Yeah, pretty
>> say it's done.
>> Okay.
>> Are we going to adopt all of these?
>> I don't know.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. I was just when you were asking
that I thought maybe that was your
vision.
>> Well, I was just
>> um um Dr. Aldridge, I'm hoping we can at
least have some explanation about what
they all are and then and then I'm going
to ask you all to um pick three.
We're gonna start from there and then
we'll talk about I think once we decide
about metrics and champions.
>> Great. Okay,
>> perfect. Thank you. I got ahead of
myself. Got ahead of you.
>> You didn't at all. You're
>> That's exactly. Okay, we're being
>> moving on. I'm hesitant to say the word
15th Street, but we can say it out loud.
Um
I'm talking what you had in mind here.
And I hear you when you say you want to
you want to be able to show that
something's started and then
>> that's Reed Avenue.
>> You want to start that with Reed Avenue.
>> I picked that drum to death already,
haven't I?
>> Yes.
>> Well, you said it. So,
>> but
this all looks like keeping on top of
projects and keeping things moving
forward. Continuation of both 15th
Street and Reed Avenue corridors. So,
keeping this moving. Have you all talked
about this enough this week?
>> Do we need to talk? Do we need to say
two more words? I know Larry's dying to
say two more words about it.
>> No,
>> I think I disagree I don't think I
disagree. I disagree with Mr. Escoel on
I don't disagree on finishing previous
goals and using our remaining funds. Um,
but I think if we do the pilot project
on on the lead avenue triangle, then
we're not going to have the money left
to do the big project, which is the
prominade that we promised the build the
people along there. And I would much
rather save that money for 18 months and
then do a good job for them than to
spend all of our money on a triangle and
maybe not have enough money left at the
end to build the prominade and the
amenities that are really going to
hopefully open up those those buildings
that are sitting empty and underused. So
I I guess I agree with the goal. I just
don't agree with the way that we're to
implement the goal. Um, I think the the
park to me would be the last thing that
we would do after we build the prominade
and we get all those buildings activated
then to me it would be the last thing we
do not the first time living. That's
just my opinion.
>> Has anybody talked to the business
owners? What what's their preference? Is
their preference because when I talked
to the one this morning as they were
leaving DDA's meeting, they were they
thought the park was a good start. So,
have we talked to the business owners to
see what their preference is? Anything
that moves dirt?
>> So, the sooner the better.
>> The only other thing that I heard last
night was someone mentioned that there
wouldn't be any pedestrian
traffic on the east side or the west
side. So,
>> there's not.
>> Somebody mentioned a a glass shop. Well,
that's
>> not the type of building that
pedestrians are coming in and out of.
>> That doesn't mean that in the future
that that building
would transform into something else that
would create more pedestrian traffic on
the west side of the and and I do agree
with the mayor that that provide would
be something that should be done right
away, but I don't want to wait 18
months.
That's That was my whole idea when we
>> Why? Why don't you want to wait 18
months?
>> Because it's 18 months.
>> I think we want to see something done
now.
Even if it isn't
parking lot.
Well, if I may,
what we're really the issues we have
over on the corridor go right to the the
project management, the internal report.
We wouldn't we'd be a lot further along
here if that was the case. I I think
when we're talking about the goals, we
want to see
and I'm certainly not familiar with
those uh programs that you state
employees have referenced, but if we had
a dashboard, if we had that information,
we could have a much more logical
discussion. And so I think that that's
really the point of the goal setting.
Let's set some goals that will inform us
so that we're more aware instead of
talking to each other at different
times. But I think that that's really
the goal I want to see above all else is
dashboard of projects from all
departments.
I mean, we get great stuff from CRA. We
know what they're doing.
um and and are to have that opportunity
right there. The the director is always
available. That isn't the case in every
department. And I think that's really
the goal. We should be sitting here and
come back in a year and say, "Look, we
all are talking from the same page at
least with the information. We might
disagree about it, but we're not having
areas that we really don't know that
much about. And that I I really don't uh
it gets kind of interesting when you're
questioning a department head or a uh
some of the management people about
what's going on. Um,
it would be a lot better to have a
system, and I think that's really the
goal that I want to see come out of this
is a dashboard system and a
communication plan that we can access at
any time. I mean, the technology exists.
So if we have that,
I know in particular with the corridor,
it would be very beneficial if we
weren't questioning Tom Cobb at the
meeting if we all could get to three
main points or whatever. So I think
that's my goal is to see a a system that
we can uh
take a look at. I mean there are so many
things going on and I I do understand it
would take some effort from the
departments but
it would help us so much.
>> It might save them time if we weren't
always bugging them. quite
this school. So I I just um it says
finish previous projects read out.
>> I have turned her and what a dashboard.
>> So what what do you want to see in a
goal for keeping
um
continuing with the Reed Avenue
corridor?
>> Is it just that? Is it just continuing
it?
>> I suppose at this point it's just
getting along that railroad
>> see some progress. Is it that you want
to see a plan?
>> We got a plan. I think it's just the
railroad is moving at railroad pace
which is hurry up and wait.
It's kind of like when I talk about
getting frustrated about the speed of
government. When we established, we
already had it established, but when we
funded the council contingency funds,
that's where I hear a lot of positive
feedback from the public of the things
that we've done with that and how fast
we did it.
Those projects went and got done in
three months.
They're smaller projects, but that
doesn't mean we can't use that approach
for bigger projects.
>> Mr. President, what what do you want to
talk about with this?
>> Well, I I I share I share your
>> We have a project manager.
>> Yeah. What's he doing?
>> I can tell you that. I spent an hour
wear an hour with him and tell you
exactly what he does and it isn't this
is Tom Cotton
spends well he spends 80% of his time on
open gov which has project management
modules
that we could incorporate as We deploy
opened up which we're already paying a
>> contractor for.
>> Fantastic amount.
>> So we have a contractor and a project
manager that are spending the majority
of their time on open gov.
>> Yeah, Mr. Balani is spending 80% of her
time on open.
He has a background as a database
administrator and um
we're having trouble getting a few of
the uh things to transfer over into our
historic data and uh he's made a huge
difference in
helping uh open Gov's database people
understand what we're doing and he's
helping them can't remember the name of
the uh software use um you know what
it's
um
>> starts with an S.
Anyways, um
>> people
>> in his old days, he used to do that. So,
so he's helping him write um
>> the code to fix to fix some of these
things because he understands what we're
trying to do and u so the last couple of
months he's really been very focused on
helping the building department, getting
GIS, all those kind of things to be able
to come across because he has that
background.
>> What is Michael Skinner's contract?
because it sounds like that's Mr.
Botti's wheelhouse. That might be a much
better fit than Well, because I've I
just have been expecting a project
manager to be a project manager, not to
be doing the IT coding on the back side.
But if you need him to do that, sounds
like that's where
>> it's one of the largest projects we're
doing right now. And um we've asked him
I've asked him to step in to help.
>> We've been a lot of money.
>> Yeah. And it's really important because
a lot of things we're talking about
here, um, once we get that system up and
running, there'll be a lot of modules
that will help us to meet some of these
goals. And so, but we're
it's been a struggle, but we'll get
there.
>> Do you know how close
we are to operationalizing that?
>> A lot of things
>> Well, they're huge parts of it already
in use and
>> the clerk's office and, you know, a lot
of the purchasing stuff are all working
beautifully. Building
>> finance is the next one that will go
after we get after we get the building
department finished. Finance is the next
segment that we'll work on. So we're
getting close. I mean they're using it
now, but there's certain things that
trying to help them get some of the
historical data and some GIS. Yeah.
>> Say from the GIS perspective, especially
if it's older data, it you have to do it
manually with the Excel. You gota put an
Excel and then you put it's a lot
because I did it back then when I was in
grad school. So it is a lot is it takes
months. So I can attest to that with the
GIS from experience but back in the day
used to be grad students doing it. Great
part is he understands what we're doing
as a city. He also understands the
database side and he's able to talk
between them because we would say what
they want they didn't understand. Say do
it and bring it back and it didn't work.
We tell them what we want and luckily he
understands it. So he's the he's the
interpreter right now and it's we're
making great strides right now.
>> And so this column of keeping projects
moving forward, does this really have to
do with the project management system
and tracking and a and a dashboard and
monitoring and
you see it as something different?
>> I think so.
>> Yeah, sure. I think I think they're
related.
Um,
I I've wondered at times whether we had
enough staff
on these critical big projects. Um,
>> do we only have one project manager? So,
engineering doesn't have a project
manager.
>> I mean, they they manage their own
projects out for years, but nobody
dedicated to each piece of it. The thing
the nice thing about having a dedicated
project manager is then the engineers
and the people with those skill sets can
actually be using their skills where
they're most needed. And you have a
project manager who takes that off their
plate. So then their whole job is making
sure things get done and keep moving
forward. But you have to have people
that are willing to delegate.
>> Yeah.
>> And if you've got a perfectionist,
>> that's not always the case.
which engineers
>> which we are
>> most engineers are
>> we've had several large goals that have
been going on for years
>> and we want to see them finished that's
however we get there
>> we want to see so we want to see these
>> we want to see proof that these are
moving forward yeah
>> that's what I'm seeing you say
>> it it this is just my perception it
seems like every time we take three
steps forward and we take one back. And
but we got to go back and this happened.
We got it. It's just always
we never we never meet a deadline.
>> And that's what project managers are
around. They ensure that you meet your
deadlines.
>> That's the whole job
>> on time and on budget.
>> And I think those of us who've been
around a while remember
>> Ben Horno who was the project manager.
interviews.
>> That guy came and made reports to
council meetings every month
>> and told us the status. He was good on
that project.
>> Wasn't good on our project.
>> Um and so
>> outer.
>> So the status updates that we got during
the course of that project were
outstanding.
>> We did the municipal court.
>> And so are you all looking for a
mechanism for accountability?
did.
>> Yeah.
>> Is that is that what you're looking for
a little bit?
>> Yeah.
>> We don't see progress through the our
constituents aren't seeing it.
>> And I think that's part of the problem
is then it leads to a lack of trust with
the general population because then they
say, "Well, you said you were going to
do these things, but you haven't done
these things." So,
>> and they don't know really will do these
things.
>> That makes sense. Yeah. You know, in the
legislature when that happened, we
always said, "Well, it's like watching
you make sausage.
>> Boring.
>> It's not pretty."
>> Well, I'm not sure everybody wants to
see how the sausage is made. They just
want to know that.
>> They just like the taste of the final.
>> We can combine some of those with the
accountability and being able to show
that progress is happening. Okay. I'm
going to I'm going to move on to um Mr.
Moody and Mr. White. Improve crosswalk
safety.
>> Yeah. Thank you. We were actually just
talking about that. Um,
I would say that we worked well
together, Mr. White, Mr. Lake on the
traffic safety. We were just chatting
now. We definitely got to do something
about some of these school crossroad
safety. It is dangerous out there with
some of the um crosswalks. Now, we were
talking about we need Hawk systems maybe
at some of them. We know they're
expensive, but is public safety.
Constituents are willing to say yes,
please use our money for the Hawk
system. And there was a couple roads
like GTH Avenue. I'd even go as far as
Persing and um Marty right there. That
could be dangerous. Maybe even a Hawk
system right there. And I'd say let's
get let's get some of those crosswalks
repaired again, especially at some of
the schools. I know by the crosswalk
would be like almost deteriorated. So
definitely need to do that as well too.
And even people that are, you know, just
running, riding a bike, uh, you know,
riding the scooters as well for safety,
if
>> you ever get those back.
>> Yeah.
>> But, um,
>> yeah, this this is this is a, uh, as I
said when we were going over the goal
that we had last year, this is just
another outlier from that goal and more
focused just just because of all the
tragedies that we've experienced. So we
felt that this should be a priority and
something that we thought certainly all
council could get behind.
>> Yeah.
>> Um
we role council in this this
>> Well, I think we need to play a part. We
were just informed this week that the
school district is reviving the safe
streets program after years of being
dormant. Um I think the city has a part
to play there.
Um there's also a lot of misinformation
going around. Um the district apparently
is saying that parents can't be
>> crosswalks
>> crosswalk guards and that's
>> patently false.
>> Yeah.
>> So I mean I think that the city needs to
be involved in some of these things and
>> and and
away from school districts. Larry,
I say again, 8th Avenue and and Kerry is
a huge that's a huge that's dangerous.
That's a dangerous spot. I've almost
been hit twice myself there just walking
my dog. So, um I've I have communicated
with Mr. Aan and Mr. uh Cobb. I I know
that Mr. Cobb's office is stretched
extremely thin right now, but I do think
that this should be considered as a
priority to show that we're very serious
about it. Sorry, Mr. President.
>> No, no, no. I just Is this something
that could be burned out to a private
company force taken out of the
engineering department?
>> I mean, like the hawk system. Well, I
was thinking more the crosswalks
planning
>> planning for it
>> and and implementing.
>> I'd anything that makes progress on it
or we're open to
>> I kind of echo Mr. Wolf's question. I
mean,
>> as you perceive it, what's our
involvement? How as a council, how
deeply are we getting involved in this?
Are we just passing on suggestions? Are
we forming a committee to actually
>> suggestions don't work?
>> I was I was saying
worked.
>> What's What's your vision with this goal
on how we do it? My my vision would be
to work
either contract it out and work with
that contractor and and kind of help
them establish priorities on what we see
are are problems or collaborate with the
engineering off this and try to make
measured progress on some of the things
that we've had concerns about
Because so Mr.
>> I was supposed to wait on something five
months ago crickets.
>> Do we assign the three of them to
continue that job and we
>> Well, that's to be decided. But I I'm
going back to what's our why are we
involved? It's our streets. We maintain
the signs. We maintain the crosswalks. I
mean, that's our job.
>> And I understand that, Mr. President.
It's just I don't know. I don't know
that I understand our involvement in
this part of it. Um I think they want
>> Are we directly involved or we just
saying hey we want the administration to
look at this more closely?
>> Well we got directly involved in the
enforcement
>> I know. So do we keep your committee
going and
>> Sure.
>> Okay.
>> We got what we got done together.
>> We finished our goal.
>> Yeah. You worked well together to note
too and I'm sorry to interrupt but safe
streets for all that from the no. I did
go up and talk to them a little bit when
this came up from you guys and you guys
will get that presentation sometime in
July. So that presentation will come to
you. That's when they're they're
planning to present it. So just ask for
that.
>> So wait four months.
>> Yeah. Well, you don't have to wait four
months. I just wanted to let you hurry
up and wait
>> six months.
Just just to be fair, that's that's an
NO project and I can't remember who I
can't remember who the contractor was
that the hired, but uh it was a 13-month
project because they're going to look at
all the streets that the schools didn't.
We did a one round schools. Can't
remember what that project was called,
>> but they didn't do the route. They just
did like the block of a school.
>> Exactly. And so safe routes for our safe
streets for all is going to take that
work and then look outside from there.
Um, and then, um, I know Tom has a, uh,
a contract with, um,
again, he told me, but I don't remember
the name of the contractor to look at
specifically 8th Avenue and some of the
other crosswalks that we've talked
about. They farmed that out. So, they're
actually they're being studied right
now.
>> So, Mr. President, is this one that we
should re-evaluate or revisit at our
sixmonth
time? Sure. And we've had that report.
>> Yeah. probably been 6 months when we
first did it.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> We're happy to take it on.
>> Yeah. All right. I mean, there's a lot
of existing crosswalks that just need to
be
>> sponsors
>> right out in front of the building.
I'm willing to listen with the I'm
willing to look at I mean I mean
>> Well, it doesn't exist because it's worn
off the pavement, right? I mean, the one
out in front of our building.
>> Yeah.
>> Well,
okay.
Oh, no. That would look self- serving.
>> When when you all are ready to take a
short break, just alarm.
>> I just want to tell you that my
son-in-law that is on dialysis evidently
just went in the hospital and so that I
think my phone keeps buzzing because I
think I'm getting family group messages.
So, just if you hear the buzz, that's
what's going on.
>> Okay. Thank you. Appreciate it.
>> Do you need to go do something?
>> No, he's in San Diego. He's gonna die.
He's going to die there. Oh, well I mean
that's going to check that he's on.
>> How old is he?
>> 46.
>> Yeah.
>> You want to keep going? You want
>> We'll keep going for a while. Let's go.
>> Mr. President, your goal is next.
I I guess I'm looking for
consensus on if in fact we're able to
develop some
new
funding streams. If if you all feel that
those funds since they're not
needed for today's um day-to-day work,
if you all feel that uh committing the
response to the quality of life that's
part of our mission statement to make
our city desirable is something we can
we can work towards. Uh I I truly
believe we're going to have two or three
different new funding sources.
committed accounts of contingencial
enough that we could complete some of
the major projects that CRA has been
working on. CR I gave you a list of
projects that that they have developed.
The plans are in place. They have the
master plans. They have everything ready
to go. They just don't have the funds.
>> Um in the cups
>> and and my thought process is since this
is outside of our normal
funding of
government that this would be an
opportunity for one once and for all to
create some improved I'm going to use as
an example some indoor
uh recreation. We are we live in a
climate that is so difficult for our
young people and even our even our old
people. um
to use. And so I just see this as a
one-time chance that we could really
make an impact on our community. We hear
it from the new businesses that are
coming to our community. Why don't you
have this? Why don't you have that? What
do you mean in a city your size? You
don't have a rec center as an example. I
mean, our our leads people,
>> we hear that. And so
I don't know that this will I don't know
that it will happen this year but I
think in the next 2 to 3 years this
could be a real possibility.
I would advocate that we look at using
revenue bonds and get the work done at
today's costs. Um
I believe that's dual as well. So I just
I just want to share that and see what
your thoughts are. Would it be prudent
to wait until our July follow-up meeting
when we know where we're at? I think by
July, we'll know where we're at
legislatively with funding. And I think
you'll these two projects may be further
down the road and we'll know whether
those are going to come to fruition or
not. And we'll also know what the rec
center is planning to include and what
it's not going to include. Um, you know,
so on the south side so we can
prioritize our
>> um funds that we have available. Plus I
last time I checked we have we were at
$3 million left on the sper garage. Is
that right? Two between two and three
million.
>> Two more payments.
>> Two more payments. Two annual payments.
>> Correct.
>> So um and that then that revenue bond
would be paid off. So that that would
give us a little bit more leverage with
bonding.
>> Yeah. I I I guess I just wanted to
philosophize with you and see if this is
something that
>> Mr. President Dr. So I presume if we're
doing revenue bonds
as a funding source the project you
alluded to earlier
>> it it could be
>> uh there's also another one that I'm not
at liberty to talk about. I
I I want to say I mean
when I was practicing as I've told so
many that have been around with me for a
while they're my practice was a really
good sounding board. I patients had no
that have been with me for a long time
had no qualms about telling me what they
thought about what we were doing
and and a lot of them said yeah we want
nice streets but we want somewhere to go
on those nice streets.
>> So I and we heard from Dr. Schaefer last
month about the importance of amenities
if you're going to keep young people
and that we need to grow if we're going
to survive.
Um,
you know, we lead the country in out
migration of our youth and we probably
are close to leading the country in
migration of senior citizens.
I hate to be on my generation, but
senior citizens don't do our economy a
damn bit of good.
We've already bought our houses. We've
bought our cars. We bought every tool we
ever needed.
>> We're downsizing.
>> We're downsizing. When we do spend
money, it's to go on vacation in Europe
or somewhere else as a country.
>> And it's not and as senior citizens, we
don't spend we don't add a lot to the
economy.
So, we need to have
um we amenities are important, quality
of life's important. And if it means
getting some of these things done, if we
have an identified source of income that
we can do revenue bonds,
I think we're shortsighted to not do it.
>> You know, if this list was our sixth
committee list, you'd have your public
outreach for those kids that couldn't
vote, but they'd be telling their mom
and dad.
You know, and the other thing is it's we
any of us who have had kids doing
sports,
>> we ship our we take our kids to Colorado
>> to play softball, soccer, basketball,
baseball, hockey.
>> Y
>> all year round because we don't have the
resources here. And when we're there,
>> we're paying for gas there because it's
cheaper.
>> You're getting a restaurant there. We're
shopping there,
>> staying the night sometimes.
>> Yeah. Um, so we're just completely
outsourcing revenue
because and the amount that we've
outsourced in the last 20 years, we
could have built a Taj Mahal.
>> I do have a couple thoughts on this. You
know, for me, number one priority right
now is getting new water sources. That's
a word of public utilities. We're
supportive of it. there will be more
housing and more affordable housing.
We know that we just don't have enough
quality places for people to live and
that's hurting our ability to create a
workforce. That's a statewide problem
and I think it's actually a national
problem. Housing is just a challenge for
us. Um but Dr. Renie, you know,
addressed it a little bit. 67% of our
kids when they by the time they turn 30
have left and the vast majority never
come back. The boomerang effect isn't
real. Um there's a few stories we know.
some some kids come back um you know and
and it's we should celebrate those um
70% of our college graduates leave and
don't come back and uh so we send them
out and for every three or so we send
back we get one college graduate back
you know so um it's been a challenge and
when you u when you look at it the
running business council uh in Harvard
and a bunch of people put together
report they talked about what is it that
keep people from being here but part of
that is you know sometimes kids just
want to go do something different and I
get
U part of it is that maybe some of the
jobs we have aren't what those kids are
looking for. But I think that's changing
in China. We're getting new technology.
We've got new businesses. So, we're
seeing a change. Uh then the other thing
is it's amenities. It's it's
restaurants, you know, but we don't
really control restaurants. We got bar
and grill licenses. So, we have more
opportunities for restaurants, but we
don't don't do that. But the one thing
we do do is, you know, trying to create
the qual place that businesses want to
come and invest um that employees want
to come and live and work. And for me, I
call it the dark months, but it's at six
months a year where it's dark. And um
there's not a lot to do. It's windy. It
means today it's beautiful, but we
probably wouldn't go out and do a lot
because it's just too damn windy. And so
having indoor recreation to me is
something that would be uh that we'll
get. In the last couple years, we didn't
own a gym hardly as a city. We have four
gyms now. Jason said, "Oh, that's going
to last us forever." They had so many
kids who just signed up for our programs
that now so now that we don't have
anymore. We need to build a a building
with eight gyms in it.
>> And we don't we don't have a place that
girls softball and uh soccer and those
kinds of places. We need a turf field.
>> Casper just built that new facility and
they estimate it's $20 million a year of
sports tourism that it's bringing to
their community. Um and they already had
$20 million for sports tourism from the
stuff they have. So they are they're
it's equal to what we have for Frontier
Days as far as the economic impact of
our community. So for me, if if we could
figure out a way to to build an indoor
turf field or build a big pot of gyms so
that Jason's team could program the hell
out of that where our kids wouldn't have
to go to Gillette and Casper to go to
tournaments, some of those times they
would be able to stay in their own beds
and those people come here so
grandparents could watch their kids
play. To me, I I just I think that that
would be an absolute home run for our
community. And then when these companies
come and they're like, well, do I go to
Colorado? Do I go to Utah? Do I go to
WMaker? And they come around and they
see the facilities that we have. We have
a great college. We've got great
schools. We've got the Halfway. We have
so many cool things, but we've got to
we've got to get over the top. And to
me, it's it's the lack of amenities that
that is is it's causing us to to be
struggling. And I think if we could find
a revenue source that could fund this,
we could pay on a revenue bond. There's
no limits to revenue bonds. If you can
if you can show the revenue, you can
bond. It doesn't there's no we can just
do this. And so I would love I love to
do this.
>> Dr. I I don't know that this needs to be
a goal one of our top three. I guess I
just wanted to philosophize with you and
if we can develop these new funding
streams outside of our oblig current
obligations I just want you to think
about that and if in fact that happens
and we come back and say hey we have the
ability to bond for a number of $50
million I don't know what the number is
u and we're going to use these revenue
streams is that something
Johnson alluded to that as well. I'm
sorry. Yeah, I was Yeah, I was going to
say too um I mean let's definitely let's
not forget though those who are
retirement migration people because that
is I mean Wyoming I joke is the cold
Florida because we're number three.
Yeah. So right
>> we're getting a lot of people retiring
from there and we definitely if we're
going to do these amenities we cannot
forget them because um that and I'm
looking at demographics as a geographer
that demographic is going to continue to
grow. It's not going to go down. I mean
we we're one of these states where it's
only going to continue to grow. So we
got
>> I want to live forever. So I hope we
>> oh we did build a lot of pickle ball
courts.
>> We did look at that. Isn't that amazing?
>> I will throw out Mr. President,
>> as much as I appreciate you saying it
may not need to be a goal, I I will
argue that it won't get done unless it
is.
>> Put it in a parking lot. A parking lot
for
>> July. Yeah.
>> But we don't do now, but we don't lose
if we don't make it a goal.
>> But we bring it up if by maybe July
you'll have that funding source.
>> And we know it's one of them.
>> I think it's possible we'll have at
least one of them. So some I think keep
it close. We do have a success story in
that gymnastics facility. We built it
and the state championships are going to
be here this year.
>> Well, and maybe we start kids are now
doing it.
>> We're just going to take
>> to your point and I don't want to
belabor this because I know we need to
move on, but the uh spokesperson
Mrs. Ter from the War Brown Beaches from
the War Brown Foundation did say that
while a lot of what they're are going to
building is unknown, one thing that she
did say would definitely be part of that
new project is an indoor turf facility.
>> Have an indoor walking track and a pool.
>> You're right.
>> Yeah. Well, correct.
>> Correct. Now, she said that they'll have
a gym, they'll have a pool, and they'll
have some sort of a turf facility, but
we don't know what the size and I think
they're still working on costing. Right.
>> I can tell you a full-size turf field um
in a building at least $30 million.
>> Well, they're anticipating what I was
told by her is that over $und00 million
for this building.
>> Nice.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay.
>> Mr. Wolf,
Mr. Wolf,
>> uh I'm fine with all the goals that
people have talked about.
No, your your goal of develop a citywide
strategic plan and identify people that
will be the best rece
I I have goals in life like getting
people to take their hats off in our
meetings.
So far has been successful.
Um my goals actually are
we need a government and a council
that's viewed as competent,
that's viewed as completing projects,
that is viewed as innovative,
that is viewed as cutting edge in the
use of technology,
that has a plan that you can actually go
and look at and that integrates ates not
only just the departments but integrates
all of the budget so that everything you
do is tied to a budgetary item.
I think we need to commit ourselves to
better leadership
uh at the both at the
city and in the council.
better in the sense that it is more
directed, more forceful.
And the thing about that, all of you
who've been on the council for a long
time have forgotten what it's like to be
a new council member.
And let me tell you what it's like just
for a second, which is the impression
you have is that
we're all free agents. that we have nine
free agents on the council who have
a desire and a willingness to get
involved in sort of whatever sparks
their interests, whatever their
constituents come and ask them about.
But that doesn't lead to actually very
coherent leadership
nor does it lead to coherent
accomplishment of specific goals.
So the things that we ought to focus on
are trying to be more focused,
more directed,
figure out what exactly the role of our
council is. We don't build crosswalks.
We don't build projects. We have some
really excellent staff. Question is, are
they being managed correctly?
We have really overworked people. Um,
and then we have maybe people who are
undermployed.
Um, and so we need to be looking at
that. But that's also gets back to this
question of is this council
responsibility? Do we just whisper in
the mayor's ear or the chief of staff's
ear and say, "Look,
look at your people.
Some of them need some help and
oversight, and some of them need to have
some of these projects taken off their
shoulders so that they can be managed
actually in a much better way.
So, I don't have any great goals around
that. fine to adopt these, but you're
going to hear me through the year say
we're going to make decisions. And these
last two days have been classic examples
of where
focus leadership would have made a
difference and which we didn't have. Not
to be critical of that. I talked a lot
the last two days. I'm actually tired of
talking about some of these things. Uh
but I would urge us all to think about
every time we have a controversial
decision, what's the best way to address
this? Some of this is what Dr. Renie
said, which is laying the groundwork
well ahead of time so we don't have 50
people in here all saying the same
thing. And if they come to us, they've
in fact had the opportunity to think
about what we were trying to deal with,
not just sort of tell us what worries
them about. Now, when we have a chance
to look and say, "Okay, we're going to
fix this particular resolution
that we don't have
four or five council people just going
their separate ways to try and fix it.
That we gather all those people up, we
sit everybody down, and we get to a
resolution." Those are the kinds and
those are leadership issues. And Mr.
President, those are leadership issues
for you as you assume your role. Mr.
Mayor, they're things that you can help
us with. We're going to accomplish
things. We need to do them together. We
need to help each other. We need to work
in unison.
That's my goal.
>> Okay. I
>> No. Go. No, go ahead. And then first
>> I I want to share in a uh in a a
changing an environment that changes
quickly, an environment where you have
um un uncertain funding. Um I I know at
the college we're we have a strategic
plan, but we're moving more towards
agile planning. Any of you familiar with
agile planning?
>> I've heard of it.
>> Yes.
um simply because when you have a five
and 10 year strategic plan and things
change quickly and so mo moving more
towards strategic themes
as opposed to this is this is the one
goal we're going to to concentrate on
just to give you more flexibility and
adaptability to the needs of your
environment. But but those themes, those
strategic themes that then fall down to
departments within within the city, that
that would be something I would
encourage you all to maybe consider as
you move forward.
And there's technology that does exactly
that that allows you to have plans that
are flexible, tunable, you can look at
and and
those kinds of of change.
>> Mr. President.
>> Yeah, I I would
I I think I understand what council war
is saying, but
my experience is
these
topics we bring up. We bring up because
our constituents ask us to.
I think we can have a plan. But then
we're asked, I'm asked, why isn't this
being done? So then it becomes a a goal
of mine to try to answer my
constituents.
Um, but I have to do that within the
boundaries that I'm allowed.
I'm on the board of directors. I'm not
on the day-to-day operation. I have to
take that to staff
and I may or may not get an answer back
from staff. So then I have to follow up
and it's it's a process.
Um,
as a individual councilman,
I really don't have much swing around
here. I I don't get to do anything.
I'm lucky they give me a key to the
door, you know.
So,
>> key to the door.
>> Well, now he's got a badge.
>> I don't have a badge.
>> I mean, it's it's uh frustrating.
Folks in the community think, "Hey,
you're on the council. You can get this
done." Well, I really can't. I have no
authority fights. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Then even then stuff doesn't get
done. So it's it's frustrating and I
think you'll see this as you move
forward. Um
maybe crosswalks should not be part of
our annual goal. But to our
constituents, that is a critical safety
feature in our community that we're not
completing
all over the community.
the downtown, the schools in front of
this building. So,
I love the big strategic plan,
but we get caught up in the minutia of
the dayto-day and it's hard. It's just
hard.
It's frustrating. Well, and that and I
agree, Mr. President, and I've seen it.
And so the question is, I mean, are we
is our function as an oversight agency?
I mean, are we kind of like one of those
committees in Congress that is trying to
exercise oversight over the city?
Because when you talk about crosswalks
and nothing's getting done,
that's because
somebody who was actually responsible
for that isn't apparently either they're
not doing their job or they don't have
the right incentives to do their job or
they're not being focused enough by the
administration to make this a priority.
So our function then is to sort of crack
the whip over them uh or crack the whip
over the mayor and Amber and say
crosswalks are not being attended to.
Why? Who's responsible for this?
>> And I think that's what we heard
tonight.
>> Okay. and and and that's a that's a I
think a a purely
uh that may be one of the purest roles
of the council which is to actually
perform that oversight function. Um and
so so that's that's one that's that's
one area where the council may have a
critical role. How we do that oversight
function is the real challenge. And do
we do it by as you say and as I've been
doing kind of go around and things and
and then and then it's you know it's
these serendipitous things as you talk
about people coming up and say I mean in
the last two weeks
through a totally serendipitous set of
encounters it's become clear to me that
the Greenway Foundation is a totally
dysfunctional organization of which
we're the soul sole beneficiary at least
of their actions. In 10 years, they've
raised $65,000
and it's dysfunctional because the
doesn't have the right people involved.
So, the question I've been sitting
trying to analyze by myself, is that my
job? Am I responsible for this? Are
there other people responsible? You go
talk to the people who have greenway
obligations
and they go, "Huh, that's not our job.
That's a private nonprofit." Well, it's
a private nonprofit, but then we're the
beneficiaries. That's just one tiny
little example of all the things that
are going on and and the mayor and Amber
see this every day. Uh so defining our
role and staying within that role and
staying within the bounds of what you
know makes makes sense both how much
time we want to spend on it but I mean
look at what you're doing with these
projects
that you've you've been working on. So
how did that evolve? How did you
particularly get involved in in trying
to negotiate
uh with
major corporations on major projects
of and that's probably because of your
interest, maybe because of your
expertise in certain areas. But then
when we hear that, here's here's how we
react to it, which is that all of a
sudden at some point a magic door is
going to open. You're going to walk
through it handinand probably with the
mayor and these project managers and
tell us this is the deal we've worked
out. We want you, the council, to
approve that.
And so we're going to be sitting there
going, "Okay, well, where does this fit
into the grand scheme of everything?"
And I I actually promised myself I
wouldn't I wouldn't talk tonight, so
I'll shut up.
>> I appreciate this fresh uh approach.
>> I do. I I understand part of what
Larry's saying, not all of it, but there
are transactional and there's
transformational activities
in what we do. And and I struggled with
some of this when I started a year ago
because to be really honest, I don't
care about speed limits. I think we're
go too slow.
I I don't care. I know every time I say
that, you give me that look. I don't
care about
>> speed limits are a guideline.
>> Yeah, exactly. I don't care about
crosswalks. I care about kids and I want
them to be safe. I don't want that to be
my thing. I didn't run for city council
to mess with speed limits or noise of
cars or those kind of things. I don't
that's just not where I'm interested.
What I was interested in was how do we
make sure we have affordable housing?
How do we make sure we're building those
infrastructures? How do we make sure
we've got good jobs for kids so they can
come back? And that's more that trans
transformational
rather than a transactional. And it's
been a a struggle for me to figure out
how do I wrap my brain around what I
want to do and what I got to do. So, I
get what you're saying and I was a huge
proponent and in fact I talked to the
mayor about this early on that I think
we need a strategic plan because if you
have a strategic plan then you have
goals and objectives and then you tie
your activities to your strategic plan
so you don't get mission creep and get
going on all kinds of things that have
nothing to do with this. We stay
focused. we get done what we need to do
and I looked at some of the other cities
strategic plans but I don't know how we
do that with China to be perfectly
honest I can't quite figure out how we
would do a strategic plan so I get I get
what you're saying in that there's this
kind of push and pull of what is our
role where our powers
what can we
I I I like the way you said that. Um
what I our history as a council is that
we have so many irons in the fire that
we have tried to divvy up some of the
agreed upon goals
and and you become an advocate for that.
That's not to say that another council
person can't
get involved, assist whatever they want
to do, but there are so many different
functions going on at one time that
we've kind of assigned.
>> Now, that can be transactional or
transformative or or you could work on
both. I think what we're doing on the
bellboard is probably transform
transformational. Mhm.
>> But at the same time, I've got people in
my ear saying, "You need to fix this.
You need to take care of this. My trash
didn't get picked up.
>> The potholes." I mean,
>> so I'm trying to balance both of those
>> and fit it into a system that we are
desired and sustained.
>> That's what I'm trying to do.
>> Maybe I'll do it. So
>> I think everybody comes to the council
first with a different skill set, right?
And and for a different reason. I
actually I love the transactional piece.
Now transformational, I'm okay with
that. You know, I'll work on the bell
war or whatever we're going to do, but
I'm really about the transactional piece
and connecting with the people who
elected me and the people in our
community. That's a part I really find
enjoyable and energizes me. Um whether
that's through council and coffee,
whether that's through, you know,
helping the mom today that met we met
with the city engineer about the
crosswalk and the safety around Pioneer
Park School, it's those one-on-one
things. So while I I don't see us as a
regulatory kind of oversight thing, I
see us as an advisory council that we're
we're really just the liaison between
the community and the city government
and trying to make sure that um all the
services are done and that people's
needs get met. So for me, I'm not about
strategic plans. I hate strategic plans
and they usually are just go on a shelf
and collect dust in my experience. I
can't even tell you how many strategic
plans I've been forced to be part of and
they have never been looked at again. So
I am not I'm much more about an agile
plan and I think it's more realistic
because things are changing way too
quickly. I also am not a technopobe but
I would say that there are people
probably on the council who are not as
comfortable with technology as what you
are. Um I don't consider myself
technical but by no means am I a digital
native and um I use chat GPT for a lot
of things during my day job but I am not
going to use it to make decisions. So
and so I become old school. So I think
everybody comes with their own skill set
and and it's nine different
personalities trying to get nine
different people going in the same
direction which is like hurting cats
>> as Jennifer knows.
So
>> I think we have a plan. It's just not
that strategic.
>> Yeah.
>> Like
you were shadowing Royal in that one.
>> Pete, did you want to say something?
>> That was really good.
>> That was good.
>> Yes. I Yeah. Thank you. Um, this is a
good talk we're doing tonight. It goes
right to the heart of some real
interesting issues. And Larry, when you
say, "Think back to when you got here."
>> I think back when I got here
and
offer some carriage.
>> Excuse me. Excuse me. That was a long
time. May I
may I go back to that?
It was a lot different place, but it was
a lot the same.
And I am a technophobe and I admit it
and that but at the same time the world
moves on and we need to be part of it.
it is.
You don't see my name on this list here.
That's because the sixth penny and the
fifth penny are all of our concerns. And
secondarily, I agree that a strategic
plan or some means of looking at this in
a unified way could be very useful.
I will say that we have so many plans
and for instance
safe streets for all MO
crosswalks just have to be very
important. But how do you drill down to
that
and get to we need more funding for
thermoplastic markings?
and which is in the budget of the public
works. So I am very much in favor of
a better understanding of how a city
runs and I hope that uh we all
understand that
council people and myself included in
getting back on the public uh service
committee.
I want to go up to that office on a
irregular basis
and say we're gonna be we're going to be
looking at this next week. Could you run
through this with me? How the how this
uh
document you derived from the uh our
planning documents came to be because
it's gotten a lot more complicated. So
overall, I'd say fifth and sixth penny
for sure. I'm going to do everything I
can, but
we've got these plans. I mean, and we
plan Cheyenne,
Lincoln Way. Uh the one that I really
care about that is uh eternally stalled
is over there on uh Persian by what used
to be always drug and abandoned
buildings.
So,
a better understanding of what we're to
do
and participate in as opposed to the
these plans that departments come up
with.
And we
that
Scott Royal was right. He left and he
came back and he opened up his drawer
and it was full of plans.
So perhaps, maybe I'm
crazy, but perhaps a true strategic plan
on our part
could identify and cut down on these
plans and have some direct relationship.
Direct relationship.
Okay. Well, that's my dream.
>> Actually, can I add to that if I may?
>> Sure.
>> Yeah. I've been part of in my time here,
I've been part of a couple master plans
for the DDA and couple for the Botanic
Gardens and one for the airport at least
with with the committees I've been
assigned to and
um and the peripheral to BPUs with their
consultant.
Um
but in my 27 years, there's never been
one for the city itself.
So, I don't know if that is something we
do. And I have to say I understand
some of you caring more about the
transactional and helping people. I'm
kind of on the transformational part
because I think that's how we move
forward and that's how we that's how we
increase the desiraability of of
Cheyenne and people wanting to move here
and attracting new business. We're in an
environment in the state where I think
most the legislature wants to
hermetically seal the state and see no
change and we will we will die if we
will just we will not thrive our
businesses will not thrive if we do
that. So, I mean, I've
kind of wondering and I apologize for
that, but I don't know.
You know, like I said, I've been part of
strategic plans in a lot of parts of the
city, but never an overall one. I don't
know we benefit from that but Larry we
all tend to gravitate towards what
interests us and that's kind of where
where our individual focus we kind of
settle into whatever part of the city
that that we're interested in want to
see advanced
um
some of it's you know like I said I kind
of am with Tom and Kathy I want to see
what we can do to make Cheyenne a more
desirable place for people to move to
and for businesses to come to. Um, but
as Michelle said, I mean, she really
enjoys helping people with their
complaints.
>> Bless your heart.
>> To me, it's like it's a challenge.
>> It is. I like bill collecting, so
>> great.
So, so, but I mean, we understand your
point. I don't know.
I guess I don't know. Mayor, can we or
Amber, can we somehow find out
get maybe examples of other communities
who have done MA strategic plans or
master plans? I can kind of find out.
>> I'll I'll share with you all that as I
was looking um because I I'll be honest
with you when I talked with Jennifer the
first time, I said, "Does the city have
a strategic plan because goals should
tie up to a strategic plan?" And she
said, "No." um took some some documents
from the city and had co-pilot create a
very fast strategic plan for Cheyenne
and it was really interesting to see how
it took all of the plans that already
existed and you know really quick blew
up. Um, but it but it was a lot of the
things that you're already doing in a
thematic kind of way. And so it it may
be worth exploring themes and and
because I mean you have one for the city
and then every single department should
have to have one that then connects to
>> to what that is and then and then that's
how your goals get set is is by that.
But but thematically um but it's a I
think it's a it's a healthy discussion
and it was a good question.
>> Yeah, I did the same thing. Um I asked
her to go look at Port Collins, Casper,
any other city of our size.
>> There there are many that exist
>> and and so I mean there isn't and this
is where the technology is can be
enormously useful. And you could take
every single plan that we have and some
of the departments have very detailed
plans, engineering,
Jason Sanchez, several other places and
you could put them in, but the the
anyway
it it would take some effort.
>> It it would it would probably be a
year-long effort to create
>> strategic plan for the city that you
need a consultant to probably walk you
through some of it. But
>> my thought was to give this job to
Jennifer and take him away from all of
her other jobs.
>> Should be done Monday
>> and be done tonight.
>> Right.
>> All right. We have I'm gonna I'm gonna
keep us moving. I'm going to keep us
moving just so that then we can get up
and walk around and and vote a little
bit. U Mr. Moody would um that last one
there, evaluate a report on improvements
needed for sleep maintenance. You want
to talk about that a little bit?
>> Yes. Um I don't know how many of you
guys had a chance. I did send an email
to visit the Cleveland maintenance
department there off of old happy Jack
Road there. Um there definitely I would
it was definitely a surprise there. I
would say we need to evaluate the
building if we can get a new building.
Um there are issues there like for
instance their system that they use now
for like the vehicles and that is very
outdated. It's all paper. They said you
know what about tablets and that to make
it go faster. I mean, because I was out
there and also just updated equipment.
Um, even just um the Ford program
because a lot of our vehicles are Ford,
it's not out there right now and they
want that implemented in there. It'll
make it a lot easier. I mean, this is
very vital because if we don't have a
good fleet maintenance, they have the
most upto-date there, we could have
problems, say with, you know, fire
engines breaking down and takes longer
to fix them or police cars or city
vehicles. So, I just encourage everybody
to go out there. I want to see us as a
goal. I've had people that work there
come to me to bring us to you guys and
that's why I want to make this a city
goal because there definitely needs to
be an evaluation and we got to see what
we can improve to make it better out
there for those that work in fleet mains
because they're the lifeblood I would
say of every single department in our uh
community.
>> Yeah, it's really outdated. I remember
when talking to council and coffee. They
said our new
>> ladder truck um
>> just to rotate the tires to get it in
there that that bay has to kind of go
back and forth like six times.
>> Yep.
>> Before they can actually get it parked
where they need to have it parked to
work on it.
>> Well, and some of them they're actually
working outside on because they don't
fit in that building.
>> Yes. The other piece is that I've been
in the welding shop there and in my day
job I oversee welding shops all over the
state and there is no way I would
certify that welding shop as anywhere
near safe. It it's it shouldn't be being
used quite honestly for safety reasons.
Um I think we have some major issues out
there and but it's not sexy and it's not
something that I think a six penny
ballot would probably garner a lot of
support for.
>> Oh yeah. Um, so I think we're gonna have
to figure out another way to fund it
because
>> that's again one of those things we were
talking about last night. There needs to
be a facilities maintenance ongoing plan
where you know this is what we do at one
month, this is what we do at six months.
And I haven't seen when I've met with
facilities and different people in
facilities, I'm not seeing any type of
organizational structure or systematic
structure that most facilities have that
show facilities maintenance schedules.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Here's the leadership then thing.
You're the guy, Mark, who's going to
dog this thing till through all this
year. You take it on, you go let them,
you bring this back to us, you figure
out, help them figure out what in the
world. And you do this all in
conjunction with the mayor's office and
whoever the department people are that
are managing that.
>> Okay. I'm, like I said, I've been in
contact with them. So, and I would
definitely welcome uh
>> I'm taking a tour in well Jennifer's in
a week or two that she's next week
>> she set up for me and I have a very very
good friend who works there and I know
he tells me exactly that. So again, but
this is a both
transactional issue and potentially a
transformational issue. If we could
actually we could get them a new
facility, which means, you know, land,
all the things that go along with that.
>> I wonder what their turnover is out.
>> It's actually Yeah, they're getting I
had lunch at this is one of the great
things about the employee lunch. I just
sat down and it was all the fleet
maintenance people. Yep. uh and and just
talk to them about, you know, what it
is, what their challenges are, you know,
and one of the big challenges is hiring
people.
>> Well, you can look really good with
them.
>> If you got to do that much work to fix
your truck, it's not a job. So,
>> well, the thing we're also not doing is
quite honestly, most of them uh a lot of
them came with ASSE certifications. we
haven't invested in keeping up those ASC
certifications
>> and which is automotive service
excellence. So I think there's a lot of
>> those are just the types of things that
are you know that fall through the
cracks are when money gets tight get
cut.
>> So we have to look how much money we
invest in the vehicles. Exactly.
>> Well and it's not like working on your
old truck like in the 50s and 60s. I
mean these are computer modules and it's
much more advanced than what it used to
be.
>> That's why I'm saying the four slow
green. We got to get that four program
in there. They don't have access to that
for pro Ford for program. They say it
would go a lot faster if they had that
for program there. And they have the
training by the way. They have the
training everybody.
>> Well, maybe and quite honestly, maybe we
need to look at uh not having our own
fleet maintenance anymore. I mean, if we
can't do it right, maybe we outsource it
or we privatize it.
>> Well, there are lots of companies who
have done that.
>> Yeah.
>> My my idea is we pay for the fleet
maintenance with our storm water fees.
before or after the drainage.
>> Okay. Do we have a good understanding of
all the goals that have been proposed?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. You're going to get up.
>> Dots.
>> Get your little sticky notes.
>> They are around the room.
>> You can use those dots, too.
>> You all have to vote and you have to
pick three. Pick your top three goals
that you want to bring forward.
>> Dots, right?
>> I'd rather
you
>> went to pick these up today. So for me,
dots.
>> Dots.
>> Only three. Would you like three?
>> You want potatoes?
>> Or a dot? I don't know.
>> Do I do this or this?
>> Either or. Whichever you prefer.
>> Do I identify myself as
>> That's a great
>> I think that
I want people to know where I'm from.
>> Yep. If you'd like to put your name on
your sticky note, that would be helpful.
>> Oh,
I'm sorry. I didn't say that.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> I didn't know how they stick on this
wall over here.
>> I think that's
quite
>> Oh yeah, I forgot about that one. What
>> six
marketing
>> six should be
something else
>> there you go
to finish
Oh, it's all wrong. Fell down. Wouldn't
very well need.
>> Ideas never do.
>> That's not true.
>> It's down here, but it's already got a
name on it. It's already taken.
Mr.
>> We know we know something else about
hard day. My watch told me I've had a
stressful day today.
>> Your watch told you that watchful to
that.
>> The squash told me I've had a stressful
day today.
>> I don't need a watch.
>> If you weren't stressed out,
>> yeah,
>> no such thing as a perfect job,
Jennifer. This is You're done with the
prize.
My job been crazier this week.
>> Oh, I bet.
>> Katie, bar the door, man.
>> Probably since Monday.
>> Oh, since Sunday when it appeared
social,
>> where does Barlo live?
>> Oh, Bish Pioneer.
>> She live No, no, she she lived two
blocks from my house. They sold that
house.
>> The one that you just bought like six
months ago.
>> Yes. You have another soldier.
>> That was Dick Keen.
>> I saw it for sale. Couldn't believe it.
I'm like
July.
>> They just moved in. I know
>> it's been a whole
>> Well, she's gonna think she's going to
be living in DC.
Delicious.
>> Doesn't she already have this?
No. She went to Virginia and they sold
that when she
>> took a job in North Carolina.
put mine on.
>> Oh, did you see Chuck Grace today? Uh
something about uh she left Wyoming to
go to Virginia. So
>> four years ago today she left.
>> Well, you know
water.
>> This is your break time.
>> Water.
This is
>> Did your mom make them?
>> My mom made them.
>> Dang.
>> Please tell her thank you.
>> Oh.
>> Oh, yeah. She makes lots of bacon.
She always knocks it out the doors.
And that's probably the biggest biggest
challenge of you like this.
>> Did everybody is everybody done voting?
>> Yes.
>> Oh, because you have to not and notice
it. You have to right if you need
>> before every LC board meeting we have
dinner
together with faculty that want to join
us and students or three students and it
just helps
build that relationship so much better.
I was going to I was going to let you
guys know that I uh initiated a poll
today is going out to 500 voters on
Cheyenne and what their number one
priority is for Cheyenne and the it
closes on the 20th Saturday.
>> Did you just send it out randomly?
>> It was through social media. The company
if selected the 500 random sample
>> they do a free one for us.
>> What is your number one priority for
Cheyenne?
So the Fort Collins
city council always meets for donor
department.
>> They say it helps.
>> Definitely helps.
>> Did Casper ever do anything?
>> I don't think so. Not
>> that
strategic plan G.
>> Oh, I don't know. I can
>> um Fort Collins has one. I know they've
got one. I was just curious if Carter
did one with you.
>> All right, you guys are
>> there for you.
>> Yes.
>> So that everybody wants to go home at
some point.
>> 7:30 in the morning.
>> That's right.
>> Um yeah, it's gonna have to be earlier
than that. Um Stuart Top, your top
choices are
Public education about the sixth thing
public information strategy spoon
feeding stories
and finish previous goals.
Those are the top things you want to do.
So,
does the implement project management
system fall under implementing finishing
goals?
>> It could. I like how you think.
>> I mean, it's a tactic to get to the
goal.
>> A tool. A tool. a tool, a strategy to
get to the goal. Those could be
>> I think I could argue those could be
tied into the same
>> if you could get buy in from the person
leading that project to pilot it.
But I mean it also takes time to build a
project management system.
>> So somebody's got to build it and I'm
not sure that that that entity has time
to build it.
True.
>> All the others are tied at three.
>> That's kind of that's kind of reflective
of our council.
>> Yeah, true.
>> How come CR legacy funding streams
didn't get more votes? We thought about
quality of life because
>> quality of life. We don't have
>> because we don't have in July. I might
put it there if we have a funding
stream.
>> Me too.
Show me the money, right?
>> Show me the money and then that one gets
my vote.
>> Well, and I really want to make sure
that we focused on six pennies. So,
>> so this one we said we would pay if
there's money in the future, right? So,
I'm taking it off.
>> We're but we're holding it for
consideration in July, right?
>> This is this is my parking lot. Yes.
This was a philosophical
>> paradise and I put up a parking lot
right there. I think we need more of
those.
>> I I did not put a vote on six penny, but
I think it should just obviously be our
major goal for the year by acclamation.
I think we all agree on that.
>> Yeah.
>> So, with your two votes, I would have
made it unanimous.
>> Yeah.
>> I I I think no matter what you're doing,
yes.
>> Yeah. You you are educating the public
on what these are and why they're
important.
>> Well, we're kind of committed to it now.
>> No going back now.
>> Oh, it is Thursday night, Archer. 6
o'clock
>> a week from tonight. Um it'll be handled
like our work sessions.
So, if you're not part of the committee,
you get to observe.
>> Will it be on Zoom?
I don't know. Are you sure?
>> Yeah.
>> We'll get an answer to that shortly.
>> I want to I want to stay on this one for
a second. How how will you know when
you've been successful here
>> because of the number of people or
whatever it is?
>> August 18th election.
>> The results. Yeah.
>> Maybe we should wait and not meet in
July, but meet in August.
>> It will not be on Zoom. open but it's
not just the completion of the ballots I
don't think to measure it one of the
measurements is do we have a plan have
we developed a written plan
>> for your marketing and communications
>> yeah no
>> okay
>> and I think those are part of we have we
have build build plan execute plan
commitment to the ballot and positive
discussion of all projects
Who are the champions
>> to make sure this gets done?
>> I would be one for the building the
plan. I don't necessarily want to be the
one person selling the plan.
I
>> think it's all hands on deck.
>> Everybody has to everybody has a part to
play in this.
>> We all have different spheres of
influence. Yes. Tell tell me who on this
council has a degree in marketing.
>> Doesn't come with a law degree.
>> Um
>> good.
>> I think I had a minor.
>> Uh
marketing and communications are a an
enormous specialty.
>> I have a lot of experience
>> and Well, that's good. And then you can
add it. Shouldn't we be thinking about
hiring somebody to do this?
>> We have We have a public information
officer.
>> We And he is overworked already. He his
his plate is full.
>> We need to get somebody.
>> So we need to find somebody else and
maybe we need to get out to the
community and get some people to pony up
some money. No, pony up some money to
hire somebody. And I think Mr. Wolf,
that's part of building the plan is is
what are the strategies that we're going
to to use to do that. But a couple of
you are going to have to drive that
plan.
>> So give me some names and I'm going to
start picking.
>> Well, and Councilman Wolf talked about
that in his selection process.
Commitment to the fifth and sixth penny
ballots.
>> You going to hold me to that?
>> I wrote I took notes.
It's a writing book.
>> The first thing I'm gonna go do is go
talk to Dave Tuber, whose business this
is,
>> and say, "What do you think we should
do?"
>> Well, he'll charge you about,000.
>> I heard you say you're I should write
your name down.
>> Yeah, that's fine. Sure. Right. Right.
>> How did the fifth penny and sixth penny
end up on the same ballot? How How did
this end up a perfect storm and end up
>> the fifth penny is every four years.
It's just on regardless and the sixth
penny ends when the collection when the
tax is collected. It just happened to
end this year at this time.
>> We couldn't slow down the collection.
>> So it just it just it just worked out.
>> And then the lodging tax is every four
hours.
>> So So that's also on the ballot. Why
couldn't one have been the general
election day anyone?
>> They are one is so the six pennies under
the primary the fifth be
>> that's why I said maybe we should wait
till August after the primary to have
our next goal setting session.
>> I think we got that one. We usually wait
till August
>> public information strategy factor.
>> I'll be out there. Pardon me. Probably a
mouthful.
>> Sorry.
>> I don't know that I want to be part of
making the plan, but I don't mind being
out there selling the
make you the sponsor.
me. You have to rank.
>> Okay, sure.
>> Well, this is
>> You're all tired.
>> Is this the Is this the
>> Are we combining these two? This is not
six me.
>> This is the public information.
>> This is the public information. Your
goal.
>> That was my goal.
>> Yeah. Are we combining those two? Is
that what's happening? No. No,
>> they're two separate.
>> Maybe do we have a This one's different.
>> Maybe we have to talk about what success
looks like and then figure out who's
going to help us get there.
Good idea.
>> Well, now to me success is just start
pumping out information
to the medium forms of it. And I don't
know may and that's probably one if we
agree that's what we need to start
doing.
Then I suppose I need to talk to the
mayor and Matt and see what we have to
do to implement that and I come back to
you guys and
>> still we need to have a conversation
about this though because if we're going
to do what what you guys are talking
about
I can't find out about ordinances when
they get put on the on the on the
agenda. Right? If we're going to get out
in front of these things, we need to
talk about what those going to look like
months before they go on on the the
agenda. we've got to have it so we can
do the public information stuff before I
can't tell you how many times I learned
about things when I see the agenda. And
so if if we're going to uh actually
control this, then this group is going
to have to start sharing um you know
their actions, we have to do it soon
enough so we can actually do a public
information strategy.
>> But it works both ways.
>> No, it does.
>> So
>> yeah, I always call you guys when I do
something.
>> But I'm just saying it's
>> don't call me. I try. You just don't
answer.
Uh uh no thank you.
>> But so I
>> No thank you a little about responding.
>> One of the things I'm wondering
>> Don't look at me like that. We've all
tried to email you or text you.
>> That was Friday.
>> Okay. Stop. Stop. Stop. Stop. Stop.
>> It's Friday.
>> How are we going to know if this is
successful?
>> I I have an idea.
Um I belong to several organizations
where they had take their board members
and each board member signs up for a
different topic for a different a
different month. And I know Pete has
been good about this. Richard Johnson
was good about it writing editorials. Um
but I'm wondering if maybe we um divide
up the work. I I mean all of us have a
different style, right? And so, um, one
of the pieces of legislation that I'm
getting ready to release. I've been
working with getting with the family is
about public memorials. And I've been,
um, in contact with the family for the
young woman that was killed on Nationway
5 years ago. So, um, and that probably
will be ready. I mean, it's already
ready with the city attorney. I just
asked him to hold off until I could get
a hold of the family. That's the type of
thing that we probably need that would
be good for like a a piece to let the
public know in advance so that they
aren't blindsided by that because I
think they feel blindsided sometimes.
>> Um so maybe we
develop a list of topics that we are
working on or planning to work on and
then or maybe sponsors take on that
responsibility. I don't know what that
plan looks like, but I think if we
divide up the work, I don't know that
quite honestly, I don't know that I want
somebody on a piece of legislation I'm
writing or working on, I don't want to
assign that to an intern or to a public
information officer or somebody else to
write about.
>> Okay.
>> How about some of the internal stories
that I'm thinking about the the one you
gave as mayor with the cameras?
>> What cameras?
>> I mean, we wouldn't have notice of those
kind of things.
>> I think the timing on that right now
would not be more more news article than
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And now I if
How about if I meet with Patrick with
the mayor and with Matt and just kind of
figure out
>> sense
>> a strategy that might work for us and
I'll bring it back to you guys.
>> Matt, may are you okay with that?
>> Yeah, for sure.
Everybody else all right with that?
>> I'm good with that.
>> How will you bring it up back to us?
>> You know, we can either have another
meeting or
>> Oh, we know if that's successful when he
brings it back to us.
>> How will you measure that?
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Come up with a baseline and we can
either agree or not. I think that but I
also think the measurement is that it I
mean we maybe avoid some of the issues
that we've dealt with from the past.
>> I think developing a process for how
you're going to share information in in
an effective way. developing that that
process that will be key to then how you
how you all um follow that process and
are able to communicate with each other
to get ahead of things
>> because it could be like without
drowning that four weeks before you plan
on releasing a resolution or ordinance
you let the mayor know.
Um, and then that gives Matt
four weeks time to loan,
>> right? Or somebody time. I mean, I
understand I understand Michelle's point
that if she's if it's proprietary
essentially to her,
>> I just wanted the family to know about
it first. I
>> No, I get that. But I mean, doesn't
matter on the issue. If for you it's
proprietary, you want to have control of
the message, then I guess we I don't
know. We'll figure out. And it wasn't
until the mayor told me that I did not I
did not realize until just recently when
we visited that I just assumed that the
city attorney shared with him the things
he was working on for us and it doesn't
work that way.
>> Interesting. So
>> clear this year
>> but I never I never thought of us as
being different clients.
>> So
>> he doesn't share with
>> Did you know that Kathy?
>> No. See
>> no I didn't I didn't either. So
>> like to me this almost sounds like an
adox committee that could work together
and p and power this out.
>> And you know we could maybe start as a
goal is you know to try to the number of
articles we do in a month or something
like that just as a simple
>> I think your goal is to develop a
process.
>> Yep.
>> Yes.
>> Does that include who's going to work on
the social media aspects of all that
stuff?
>> I think we need I think that should be
part of your
>> part of your process.
Well, it's
>> and and strongly consider internship and
I can you know quite a few thousand
students that might help with that.
>> If you can find us a you find us a
couple.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely. If you want to
create an internship, we can find you
people.
>> So I don't I think Facebook's for old
>> Yeah. Now I don't think
>> but those are a lot of you need a
Snapchat for the young people.
>> People I mean myself like
My daughter tells me she's 28
Tik Tok and Instagram. Dr. Jenny, will
you be a part of this group to help
develop the process?
>> Yeah, I thought that's what
>> Who else?
I only volunteered the mayor and Matt to
do it. So, I hope anybody else wants to
meet with us.
>> So, where does Gen Z and Gen X get their
use? probably Facebook
>> and no Facebook and over
>> Tik Tok.
>> Um Instagram,
>> Tik Tok and Snapchat.
>> Okay,
>> but that's their
age.
>> I'm sold.
>> How many do you have?
>> How many?
>> I have both.
>> You use them?
>> Where? Oh, I don't use have people said
>> Okay. Are we Are we good with these?
>> Yeah. We have a direction
>> and then
finish previous goals.
>> These are already in in existence.
>> Well, I I would I was voting on finish
previous goals Reed Avenue.
>> It's just staying on top of the things
we have
going on like
making sure they actually get done.
Well, Pete, I you know, Pete and Jeff
and I are are watching and working on
Reed Avenue all the time. Uh 15th Street
is
uh one that, you know, we need to keep a
close eye on.
uh and uh we will um you know that
because it ties into the DDA, it ties
into the deeper museum, it ties into all
the other things and and the six penny
too.
Those are the sort of two big core
downtown issues.
>> So I I have a clarifying question and
maybe it's really just for myself. It is
the goal really
these two things or
monitoring monitoring and reporting out
progress on these.
>> So we have the pump house was another
previous one that that we've been
working on. We're getting close to
there. We have we have some ones that
have been lagging for a few years. Our
annexations were within six months or a
year from those being done.
So maybe
project management system
>> so that we can monitor track.
>> Yeah. Well, I think Tom and his crew and
some other people sitting down and and
helping us build something that would be
useful. Um,
it may be though that there's already a
tool there that's just not being
utilized
>> or maybe we just don't know about it.
>> Yeah, that defined
a dashboard with it. Well, I Tom has all
of this all of these projects on very
very detailed timelines and plans and
and you saw that in the two memos we
got. Um but yes, having it someplace
that it's actually accessible to other
people
>> and accessible to go talk to Tom and um
is great.
because I I keep hearing what what
you're saying is a a way to report out
on existing projects.
>> I think what I'm hearing is just
frustration about not knowing the
progress or the status more than
>> Yeah.
I think that's a lot of being able to
discuss it when you're asked about it
and
I don't know what we're at. I think
that's
>> and so is that really exploring a
mechanism to to make you all better
informed on existing projects
>> and then if they don't see a progress
and they don't need to push a little bit
but there
>> Oh god. And it isn't just
>> it isn't just us. I mean, it's it's
>> if if one of the businesses downtown
wants to know what's going on with 15th
Street, it would be great to be able to
direct them to a location on our website
um that they can actually educate
themselves about it.
>> And so, I think that may come back to
the
Where's our system? Is this our project
management process process system?
>> Um and exploring a way to do that.
>> Yeah.
>> No.
>> And Larry, you said you think it already
exists in open.
I I mean I've got to believe there are
project management module that we can
purchase in
>> for the thousands of dollars.
>> We may have already
we've spent
>> open
place
>> paper
>> paper.
Yes.
>> Yes. the graphite.
>> Honestly, he couldn't do a he couldn't
do a building permit or anything online.
Everything was had to come in and give a
check.
>> Is is it more important that this is
do you do internal first or external
first? Which is more important?
>> Internal.
>> So that we know
>> you can't sell anything externally if
you don't understand it internally.
I think
>> I know that but I want to hear you say
it.
>> Okay.
Who's our champion here?
>> Suggest.
>> I'll be happy to help you.
>> I'd be glad to help you, too. I mean, I
actually have a better experience with
it.
>> Kathy, Michelle, Jeff, and Larry.
>> And we still have our revenue subject.
>> Can I come by your office and have you
show me the drills?
>> Yeah, we can even do uh Can you do a
Google Meet?
>> Yeah,
>> I can even set it up.
>> Never done Oh, I'm sure I've done one,
but
>> we we can set it up so I can show you
over the screen. So, it's actually
>> You can do like a shared screen and and
walk you through it.
>> Do that. Just send me send me an
invitation. We'll do it together.
>> Sit down with Katie too and have her
explain to you how.
>> Okay. So, I would say this one
>> these two with the understanding that
when you have a system,
>> these are some of the things you will be
reporting on the progress of these.
>> Absolutely.
>> Which already exists. We we just need to
know more about what it is. Yeah.
>> This will help us see that happen.
>> Okay.
>> That's what I'm hearing.
Yeah,
>> we can do that.
>> Okay,
>> look it up.
>> Jennifer and I will write these up and
send them all to you by 7:30 in the
morning to probably
>> Matt's already got them up.
Okay, no one's died. We're good.
>> Sun's going to come up tomorrow. Hey, I
did want to say that there is a um a
free Trello you can sign up for and
download as an app. We use it at our
house for Andy's to-do list
>> and I put everything I want him to do by
room on this list and then he checks it
off as he gets it done and then I don't
have to nag him.
>> That works. Amazing.
>> Yeah. Don't tell that to yourself.
>> Don't tell that.
>> It works amazingly.
So that's good ideas.
Amber's going to have that in my office.
You know, Patrick, you haven't done your
your trillo.
>> It's actually
>> Thank you. Thank you.
>> Everything for class 30 seconds have
been brilliant.
>> Okay. Okay. Great.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you for being very honest and
respectful conversations. That that was
on all of you. So, good good job you
guys. Okay. Well, we'll sum up Jennifer.
You'll help me summarize these down fast
and we'll send these to you all
>> tomorrow. Okay.
>> Thank you all. It's been a long long
week.
>> Yeah. You guys we have a new meeting
tomorrow and then we have some fun with
Chile. So,
>> yeah. Thank you for being a part of the
as the president of the board of the
boys and girls club. Thank you for being
a part of the chili club.
>> Are you judging?
>> I am not judging. I will be the token
villain tomorrow. You won't miss the
>> but but it's it's one of my favorite
events. So I'm I'm excited that to try
the green chili and and
>> a little bit more left over
>> and see what you all do.
>> Mr. Labour makes a great red chili.
>> Red chili green.
>> Good work on all of you. Good job.
>> Good job.
>> Thank you. Thank you Jennifer.
>> Thanks Dan. Yeah, maybe February
honestly I think I'm gonna close
meetings over there.
>> Thank you.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Talk about myself first.